<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vanity of self-boasters, or, The prodigious madnesse of tyrannizing Sauls, mis-leading doegs, or any others whatsoever, which peremptorily goe on, and atheistically glory in their shame and mischief in a sermon preached at the funerall of John Hamnet, gent. late of the parish of Maldon in Surrey / by E.H. Minister ...</title>
            <author>Hinton, Edward, 1608 or 9-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 163 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70235</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2066</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7444</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12089915</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12089915</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53814</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70235)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53814)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 240:E70, no 25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vanity of self-boasters, or, The prodigious madnesse of tyrannizing Sauls, mis-leading doegs, or any others whatsoever, which peremptorily goe on, and atheistically glory in their shame and mischief in a sermon preached at the funerall of John Hamnet, gent. late of the parish of Maldon in Surrey / by E.H. Minister ...</title>
                  <author>Hinton, Edward, 1608 or 9-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Bishop for S. Gellibrand ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Edward Hinton.  cf. BLC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms LII, 1 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53814:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE VANITY OF Self-boaſters. OR, The Prodigious madneſſe of tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing <hi>Sauls,</hi> miſ-leading <hi>Doegs</hi> (or any others whatſoever) which peremptorily goe on, and atheiſtically glory in their ſhame and miſchief.</p>
            <p>IN A SERMON Preached at the Funerall of <hi>John Hamnet,</hi> Gent. late of the Pariſh of <hi>Maldon</hi> in <hi>Surrey.</hi> BY <hi>E. H.</hi> Miniſter of the ſame, and late Fellow of <hi>Merton Colledge</hi> in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Sen. Hyppol. Act. 1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Quod non poteſt, vult poſſe, qui nimium poteſt.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Biſhop</hi> for S. GELLIBRAND at the Brazen Serpent in Pauls Church-yard. 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:53814:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53814:2"/>
            <head>Amiciſsimo juveni Ioanni Hamnet Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſo, ornatiſſimi viri Ioannis Hamnet nuperrimae de Maldon apud Regnos Suthreios Gen. filio unico &amp; haeredi, S.</head>
            <p>ROgaſti ut a me concio haec (rogo &amp; ego ut a te pater tuus) exſcriberetur, optatum jam habes, utinam &amp; ego pariter felix, hoc enim mihi unicum in votis, juxta &amp; precibus, at ipſiſsimum patris prodeas exemplar, ut ſis non rei familiaris tantum, ſed &amp; virtutum haeres, ut emorituri parentis, jam jam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ultimum emittentis ſpiritum, coeleſtibus planè oraculis &amp; fidem habeas &amp; morem geras; ſic te tibi reddas, ſic tecum vivas, ſic proprio ſinu, domique ſenatum, aerarium, &amp; exercitum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas, ſic Deo proximior fias, ſic amico.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>E. H.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Mald. pridiè</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Calend. Iul. An. ſalutis, 1643.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:53814:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53814:3"/>
            <head>THE VANITIE OF Self-boaſters: OR, A SERMON Preached at the Funerall of <hi>John Hamnet</hi> Gent. late of the Pariſh of <hi>Maldon</hi> in SURREY.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 52.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Why boaſteſt thou thy ſelfe, O mighty man in miſchiefe? the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Lord endures for ever.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was much folly in the Stoicks, to hold that all ſinnes were equall, none of a greater ſtain or poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon then another; but 'tis ſtupidity in the Papiſts, to make the gap ſo wide as to affirm, ſome to be veniall onely, and the other mortall; If the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts were in the right, then <hi>every ſoule which ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſhould not dye,</hi> 
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 11.20.</note> if the Stoicks, then <hi>ſhould it not have been ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier for Sodom and Gomorrah, then for that City:</hi> 
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.15.</note> Every ſinne doth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53814:4"/>
               <hi>lineam tranſilire</hi> (as <hi>Cicere</hi> expreſſes it) is a tranſgreſſion of the Law, and that is death; then none is veniall; thus the Papiſts erre: and if every ſinne is a tranſgreſſion of the Law, then <hi>Longè progredicum ſemel tranſieris, auget tranſeundi culpam</hi> (as the ſame Orator:) and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon tells us, the growth and continuance of ſinne make an inequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and thus the Stoicks erre.</p>
            <p>Nay, every vertue being a quality, hath its latitude, whoſe medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um is not [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] a ſtrict Arithmeticall meane, but [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] a Geometricall meane, which proportionably va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries its diſtance according to the diverſity of circumſtances: <note n="(c)" place="margin">Ariſt, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> What differences then and diſproportions are there between vices, which are therefore vices becauſe they have no mean? Yes (doubtleſſe) an ill ſuggeſtion quickly ſtifled is not ſo bad as that which is nouriſht into a thought, nor this thought as bad as ſuch a one, which growes up into the mouth, and breakes out in words; nor this neither ſo ſinnefull, as that which ſets the head a plotting, and the hand a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king miſchiefe; nor this plotted, active miſchiefe ſo black and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as a wicked habit wallowed and delighted in; nor hath this wicked habit ſo much death and wormwood in it, as when it is ſwoln to ſuch a bulk, come to ſuch a <hi>non ultra</hi> as to be boaſted of; for lower then this canſt thou not ſinke, unleſſe thou ſinkſt into hell and takeſt <hi>Iobs</hi> wifes advice, curſeſt God and dyeſt. Again, not to love and pray for our enemies is a very ſinne, a breach of our Saviours in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.44.</note> but a greater ſinne is it to withhold our love and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers from Gods beſt Children, and holieſt ſervants; but worſer is it to hate them; but yet farre worſer, to be an inſtrument of their ruine; but worſt of all, (and horror to imagine) to triumph that thou waſt thus miſchievouſly imployed, to boaſt that thou didſt hatch the plot that ruind them, diſchargedſt the Cannon that tore them, madeſt the pill that poyſoned them, waſt a <hi>Doeg</hi> (a knight of the Poſt) which didſt accuſe and butcher them. Laſtly, of all ſinnes, pride and boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting have the blackeſt brand, and of all boaſtings a boaſting in miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe; and of all boaſtings in miſchiefe, a boaſting (O thou migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty man, or) that thou art mighty in miſchiefe Well then may <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> in wonder and amazement, or I in his perſon, aske <hi>Saul</hi> the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutor, or <hi>Doeg</hi> his informer, and executioner, his bloody miſlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding inſtrument, or any other incarnate Devill peremptorily trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing in the blood or fall of Gods people, <hi>Why doſt thou boaſt thy ſelfe O mighty man in miſchiefe? the goodneſſe of the Lord en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53814:4"/>for ever.</hi> This paraphraſe for the explanation of the words. Take another, whereby wee may know the occaſion of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> was now an innocent perſecuted Dove (as you have the Hiſtory, (1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21, 22.) who willingly would have returned with an Olive branch in his mouth, for <hi>hee ſought peace, but they would have warre</hi> 
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 120.7.</note> Wherefore finding the floods ſtill up, the <hi>waves encompaſſing him on every ſide, which made him afraid</hi> 
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.4.</note> And having no quiet place, no whereto reſt his foot on, he returnes like <hi>Noahs</hi> Dove to the Arke, betaked himſelf to <hi>Abimeleth</hi> the Prieſt of the Lord for advice and ſuccour; who beleeving him faſt both to God and the King (though the king was not pleaſed to think ſo) did not ſtick, in caſe of neceſſity, to break a ceremony, gives him the hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed bread and <hi>Goliahs</hi> ſword: But ſee the miſchiefe, the Devill (as u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually it falls out) had ſent a <hi>Doeg</hi> (who even in Gods Temple was his Chappell) to gather pretence of ſlander and death againſt them, who preſently carries and aggravates the buſineſſe to <hi>Saul; Saul</hi> being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore heated, was now on fire, turn'd his former rage into madneſſe, (ſo quickly doth a bloody tyrannicall nature kindle at the leaſt hint) he forth with ſends for <hi>Abimelech,</hi> and making his will his Law, becomes himſelf: both the accuſer and the Iudge, and makes <hi>Doeg</hi> his informer his ſpeedy executioner, who forth with falls on <hi>Abimelech,</hi> and for the reliefe he afforded the Lords ſervant and his own faithfull ſubject, ruines both him, his family and City. Had not <hi>David</hi> then, think you, juſt cauſe to be thunder-ſtruck at the confident and peremptory proceeding of the tyrant <hi>Saul,</hi> or his bandog <hi>Doeg,</hi> and in amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to cry out, <hi>Why doeſt thou boast thy ſelfe O mighty man in miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief? the goodneſſe of the Lord endures for ever.</hi> This the occaſion of the words.</p>
            <p>I will not raiſe a quarrell by telling you how Expoſitors wrangled and are divided about my text, how they turn and alter both the ſenſe and words, becauſe though they ring as it were changes on them, and ſet the words ſeverall wayes, yet (like skilfull Muſitians) they keep the Muſick ſtill ſweet, and the tune good. Notwithſtanding I ſhould much wonder how the Papiſts ſo conſtant to their old Tranſlation, which they call St. <hi>Hieromes,</hi> ſhould here leave it and follow the Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuagint, did I not know they gladly take any occaſion to baulk the Originall. The words are, as you already gueſſe, a Queſtion by way of admiration, <hi>Why dost thou boast thy ſelfe O mighty man in miſchiefe?</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:53814:5"/>and the ground or reaſon of that queſtion <hi>[for the goodneſſe of the Lord endures for ever.]</hi> The Queſtion naturally and of it ſelf falls into theſe 3. Queſtions:
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Why doſt thou boaſt thy ſelfe?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Why doſt thou boaſt thy ſelfe in miſchiefe?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. and laſtly, <hi>Why doſt thou boaſt thy ſelfe in miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief O thou mighty man?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
or that thou art mighty in miſchief? all which the ground and reaſon of the generall Queſtion doth make good; and ſeverally anſwer: ſo that the burden of the 136. Pſalme might very well be the burden and keeping of my diſcourſe; Thus:
<list>
                  <item>1. Why doſt thou boaſt thy ſelfe in any thing? <hi>for the mercy of the Lord en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures for ever:</hi> whatſoever thou haſt, 'twas his mercy that gave it thee, and 'tis the enduring of his mercy that continues it.</item>
                  <item>2. More eſpecially I wonder, <hi>Why thou doſt boaſt thy ſelfe in miſchiefe,</hi> glory in thy ſhame, to ſee thee thus daring I am at a loſſe, ſcarce my ſelf, for know again, <hi>the mercy of the Lord endures for ever:</hi> 'tis the enduring, the continuance of his mercy that thou art not blaſted in the midſt and heat of thy pride and miſchiefe.</item>
                  <item>3. I moſt eſpecially wonder, why thou doſt boaſt in miſchiefe O thou mighty man, or that thou art mighty in miſchiefe; to ſee thee ſo deſperate I leave to be man, have almoſt as little of reaſon in me as thou haſt of God; for once more know, <hi>that the mercy of the Lord endures for ever:</hi> notwithſtanding the blood and Croſſe of the Saints be thy thirſt and pride, yet know, <hi>as for Iſrael,</hi> as for them, <hi>the Lord of Hoaſts, the Lord is their memoriall,</hi> the great and conſtant love of God will in the fitteſt time relieve his ſheep and repay their wrongs. <note n="(g)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.5.</note>
                  </item>
               </list>
But I muſt ſuit my diſcourſe to the ſad occaſion of our meeting, nor will the ſhort warning for my medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or the ſcantling of time allowed me for their delivery, ſuffer me to be thus exact. For the generall Queſtion broken into theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars doth juſtly challenge more then an houre for the handling of each of them ſeverally. At this time therefore onely of the 2. former Queſtions. And (truth is) I have been therefore the larger in para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſing and opening the words, that you might be the better conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to give me leave to deferre the laſt Queſtion to ſome other oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity. Now for the firſt Queſtion, beſides the ground and Reaſon in the Text, which (to ſpeak truly) doth more properly make good the two other Queſtions; we have 3. other grounds and reaſons, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to which this 1. Queſtion will alſo multiply. The 1. ground and reaſon is the lowneſſe, weakneſſe and nothingneſſe (as I may ſo ſpeak) of the party boaſting, whether <hi>Saul, Doeg,</hi> or any other; and then the 1. Queſtion will be, Why doeſt thou poore, fraile, nothing man why
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53814:5"/>doſt thou boaſt thd ſelfe? The 2. ground and reaſon is the uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, emptineſſe, and vanity of that which neceſſarily muſt be the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of ſelf-boaſting; and then our 2. Queſtion will be, Of what doeſt thou boaſt thy ſelfe? The 3. and laſt ground and reaſon, is the fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and foolery of the end of ſelf-boaſting, <hi>viz.</hi> the froathy applauſe of the giddy multitude; and thus our 3. and laſt Queſtion will be, To which end doſt thou boaſt thy ſelfe? Of theſe in their order, and firſt of the firſt, Why doſt thou poore, fraile, nothing man, why doſt thou boaſt thy ſelfe?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>1</label> If we truly weigh our ſelves, what have wee which might either juſtifie a fooles boaſt, or tempt a wiſe mans? No creature doth it ſelfe ſo little good when firſt it comes into the world, nor ſo much harme, whilſt it continues in it, as man: <hi>Caetera animalia mihi natur â potiùs quàm ratione artem aliquam exercere videntur, ut formicae &amp; apes; homo verò ſicut corpus armis nudum ſic &amp; animum artium deſtitutum habet,</hi> 
               <note n="(h)" place="margin">Ga'en de uſu par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium l. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> (as the Phyſician.) Other creatures ſeem naturally to exerciſe a kind of art, as the Bee and Emmet, but man, as he hath a body void of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall weapons, ſo alſo a mind void of naturall arts; and although <hi>Galen</hi> immediately addes <hi>[Quòd pro corporis nuditate manus, &amp; pro ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium imperitiâ rationem accipit]</hi> that his hands ſupply the want of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, and reaſon recompenceth the want of arts, yet his reaſon (though naturally <hi>[ſaniſſima]</hi> never ſo ſound and acute (ſay <hi>Socinus</hi> what thou wilt) if not firſt <hi>[ſanata]</hi> bent and rectified by the Holy Ghoſt, is no better then a ſword in a mad mans hand, wherewith whilſt hee lives he doth himſelfe more harme then any other creature is capable of. Heark what low thoughts my kingly Prophet had of man, <hi>Surely every man at his beſt eſtate is altogether vanity,</hi> 
               <note n="(i)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 39.5.</note> Hee ſayes not that man is vain onely, but vanity it ſelfe: and <hi>[Abstracta ſunt ſignifican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiora]</hi> Abſtracts are weightier and come more home. 2. He excepts none from being vanity it ſelfe, Every man is vanity: <hi>Neminem ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipit, ne quem decipiat,</hi> ſaith a Father <note n="(k)" place="margin">Auſtin.</note> Hee excepts none, becauſe he would deceive none. 3. Not every man onely, but man in every e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate and degree, is vanity it ſelfe; yes at his beſt eſtate he is ſo. 4. He is vanity it ſelfe in every both part and faculty of ſoule or body, for he is vanity (ſaith he) altogether. 5. and laſtly, all this (it ſeems) is a very certain truth, otherwiſe he would not have affirmed it with this ſerious aſſeveration <hi>(ſurely)</hi> ſurely man is vanity it ſelfe, every man is vanity it ſelfe, every man at his beſt eſtate is vanity it ſelfe; Yes, every man at his beſt eſtate is altogether vanity it ſelfe. I know not what
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53814:6"/>might be more ſaid to coole and damp the ſwellings and excreſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of proud man.</p>
            <p>Our ſad and miſerable condition in this world cauſed (as ſome have well conceived) that fond opinion [of mens ſoules] to get with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the wiſeſt of Philoſophers; which, ſay they, had from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their creation and being in heaven, and for certaine faults there committed, were ſent hither to be impriſoned in fleſh, to be wrackt with its paſſions, and to undergoe the multitudes of miſeries, which unavoidable ſeize us. Nay, the thought and knowledge of the poore and wretched eſtate of man brought alſo this errour into Divinity; for I have read of a ſect of Hereticks, called <hi>Origeniſts,</hi> who were of the ſame opinion with the Philoſophers, who wee may well thinke were ſo called from <hi>Origen</hi> the Father, becauſe I find <hi>Auſtin</hi> bringing him in ſpeaking almoſt the ſame words <note n="(l)" place="margin">Animas fuiſſe olim in coelo an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelos, qui in coelo pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jiciuntur in haec corpora quaſi in ſe pulchra; &amp; tot in coelo ruinae, quot in terra na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivitates, Ep. Tom. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>124.</hi>
               </note> This conſideration alſo made the <note n="(m)" place="margin">Nat. Hiſt. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>63.</hi>
               </note> Naturaliſt conclude it an argument of natures bounty afford us ſuch diverſity of poyſons, whereby we may free our ſelves from the world and its croſſes. And though Religion allowes not of this atheiſticall exchange of miſery, of leaping out of the Frying<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pan, as we ſpeak, into the fire, even Hell-fire; yet the miſerable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of man hath made ſome of the Fathers to beſtow large-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations on death; that known ſpeech of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> is moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, <hi>Mors remedium potiùs poenae, quàm vindicta culpae;</hi> Death was brought on us rather for the ending of our puniſhment then for the puniſhment of ſinne: For a puniſhment, ſaith he, was it ſaid unto man <note n="(n)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>In the ſweat of thy brow ſhalt thou eat thy bread;</hi> but for his comfort was it added, <hi>till thou returne to the earth:</hi> And even in this reſpect alſo is it truly affirmed by our beſt Divines, that though death conſidered according to its owne nature, be a puniſhment; yet as it is conſidered with relation to the faithfull, it is not, becauſe to them the nature of it is changed, and from a curſeit is turn'd into a bleſſings for the ſting of it Sinne is taken away, in which its hurt and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment conſiſted; and whereas <hi>Arminius</hi> would therefore prove death properly a puniſhment even to the faithfull, becauſe though the right of holding them captive be taken a way from death by Chriſt, yet from the actuall dominion of death we are not freed till the reſutrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I could tell him (might I ſtay ſo long) that death hath not this actuall dominion over the faithfull (he ſpeakes of) ſeeing by Chriſt we have gotten the victory over it; ſo that we may not crouch to it as captives to their Governour, but rather as Conquerours over a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53814:6"/>captive may we triumph (<hi>O death where is thy ſting?</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55.</note> thy puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, thy dominion?) thought thou art an enemy, the laſt enemy to be deſtroyed, and art though by the Arminians to helpe forward our afflictions, yet abundantly haſt thou helped forward our good, the good not only of our ſoules, which hereby flye to heaven, are made infinitely and eternally happy, but of our bodies alſo, which hereby have a thrice happy deliverance. Firſt, they are delivered from the ſenſe of miſery, from the paines of ſickneſſe, the troubles of old age, the croſſes of the world, and the miſuſages of perſecutors. Secondly, they are delivered from the ſociety of wicked men; they are tooke from ſojourning in <hi>Meſech,</hi> and from dwelling in the Tents of <hi>Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar,</hi> which in this world is ſo loathſome, ſo burdenſome unto them, Thirdly, &amp; laſtly, they ceaſe from their labors, not only from their ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, under which they unavoidably labour, but from their labours of ſinne, they reſt from their workes of wickedneſſe: ſinne by death loſeth not onely its dominion, but its habitation, it ſhall not onely not reigne, but no longer dwell in their mortall bodies, and the reaſon is, becauſe their bodies ſhall be no longer mortall.</p>
            <p>'Twas well askt, why is earth &amp; aſhes proud? <note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ecclus</hi> 10.9.</note> ſo true is that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon etymology, <hi>[homo quaſi ex humo]</hi> man is ſo cald, becauſe his foundation is in the duſt, <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 108.9.</note> our firſt parents had no other materials, nor ever ſince have we: nay the bowels whence we ſprang are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe [<hi>Wonderfully and fearfully</hi> (<hi>ſayes the Pſalmiſt</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 15.</note>) <hi>haſt thou made me in the nethermoſt parts of the earth</hi>] <hi>i.</hi> in my mothers womb, and ſo (truth is) the Chaldee Paraphraſt reads it: hence the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes call women plainly earth; ſo truely, ſo verely earth are wee, not onely made of earthy materials, but caſt alſo in an earthy molde.</p>
            <p>So earthy and mouldring, that that which we call life, is it ſelfe but a waſting and dying, a continuall fluxe and decaying, no part of it being our own, nay no part of it being but <hi>[punctum continuationis]</hi> the [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] the preſent moment, which too is ſo neare nothing, that (as the Philoſopher) <hi>deſinit eſſe antequam eſt;</hi> it begins almoſt not to be, before it is. What is paſt of this we call life, is loſt, what is to come is not gain'd, this preſent inſtant onely remaining, which was ſo fleet to that 'twas gone aſſoone as I could tell you 'twas come, is vaniſh't, whilſt 'twas ſpoke of. Be not miſtaken, death conſiſts not in the laſt gaſpe, laſt groan, or fit; theſe do not name or cauſe death, but finiſh it: juſt as it is not the falling of the laſt ſand in this glaſſe,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53814:7"/>which makes or names this houre, but the falling of all the ſand; and the houre might be then ſaid to make toward an end, when the glaſſe was firſt turned. 'Tis not, you know, the laſt blaze of a Candle, ſpends him, becauſe he is ſpending all the time he burnes, and may true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſaid even then to begin to go out, when he was firſt lighted. No otherwiſe is it with us, death conſiſts not in the laſt breath or ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, no, 'tis now upon you, even upon the beſt and healthieſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, every breath you fetch, every ſtep you move, and every journey you take, 'tis towards the grave, thither were you tending, when you firſt ſet out, even the firſt minute of your birth; all of you beginning then to die, when you firſt began to be.</p>
            <p>But men reſolving to be proud, <note place="margin">A Cavill anſwered.</note> and therefore willing to forget they are but duſt and aſhes; may reply, 'Tis a very truth, that in theſe times and places of Warre and ſickneſſe, our earthy fraile condition plainly appears; but at other times, and in other places, we know 'tis otherwiſe. Have there not bin, and are there not even now amongſt us many aged people? <hi>Anſw.</hi> 'Tis confeſt, but yet there is ſcarce any of theſe aged ones, which you call now living, which on ſerious thoughts and recollection dare ſay they truely live, that onely being true life which hath joy and contentment individuall with it, which the cares and thornes of the world, the weakneſſes and infirmities of old age denying them, denies them alſo truely to live. So true is that of my Pſalmiſt, <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.70.</note> 
               <hi>The dayes of our yeares are threeſcore yeares and ten, and if by reaſon of ſtrength they be eigthy yeares, then is their ſtrength labour and pain.</hi> If joy and content did not onely ſpeak us truly and properly alive, then they in hell may be ſaid to be alive, but on them the ſecond death hath ſeized. Aged men (by reaſon of the troubles and cares the world hath brought on them) are like thoſe on the ſeas, bent for a ſhort voyage, but vext and hindered by contrary winds and tempeſts: for as ſuch cannot be ſaid [<hi>multum navigare,</hi> but <hi>multum jactari,</hi>] not to faile farre, but to be much toſt: ſo old people may not ſo properly be ſaid to live long, as to be troubled long. But grant that ſome old men have beene ſo healthy and happy, that they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet taſted the bitter of croſſe or ſickneſſe, and grant that with Wine, good Company, Cardes, and a careleſſe ſelfe, loving heart they can merrily paſſe over the feares and miſeries of Church and State: grant that in ſuch franticke jollity they attaine to 80.100. yeares, yet that life is but <hi>[vapor aliquanto diuturnior]</hi> (ſaith the Father) a better laſting vapour; <note n="t" place="margin">Auſtin in Pſal. 6.</note> nay, [<hi>ſitoto illo tempore viveres, ex quo Adam è pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſo
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53814:7"/>emiſſus eſt vſque in hodiernum diem, videres vitam tuam</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>non fuiſſe diuturnam, quae ſic avolaſſet</hi>] if thou hadſt beene borne when ſinne ſlung <hi>Adam</hi> out of Paradiſe, and lived to this preſent moment, thou muſt neceſſarily confeſſe, thy life may not properly be called long, which is ſo ſwift-winged. Seeing then our life is ſo ſhort, miſerable, and uncertaine, may we not ſtand amazed at the generall pride that overſpreades and oppreſſeth the whole Kingdome, and aske almoſt every man we meet, Why doeſt thou poor miſerable nothing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, why doeſt thou boaſt thy ſelfe? And thus much ſuffice for the proofe and illuſtration of the firſt branch of our firſt queſtion; let's in the next place apply what hath beene ſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Applicati∣on. </seg>
               </label> No better uſe can we make of this firſt queſtion, and of the ground and reaſon of it thus open'd, nor any likelier meanes to take us off from pride and boaſting, then by often and ſerious meditation of our earthy, fraile, and miſerable condition to lay up againſt and to provide for death. If our life at the beſt, peaceableſt, and healthieſt times be but a hands breadth <note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.5.</note>, then certainly in theſe bleeding ſicke and worſt times, we are fallen on, 'tis not onely before God, but in it ſelfe nothing. All of us now (as <hi>David</hi> complaines <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.109.</note>) <hi>carry our ſoules in our hands;</hi> or, as our Divines <note n="y" place="margin">Ainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth in locum.</note> with the Chaldee Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſt expound him, being every day, nay every houre through the deſtroying angels of Warre, and the ſickneſſe raging amongſt us, in jeopardy of our lives, it ſhould make us again with <hi>David,</hi> (as <hi>Lorinus</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">Lorin. in lib. Sapient, <hi>6.4.</hi> v. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> and others expound him) to carry our ſoules in our hands <hi>i.</hi> with meditation of the certainty of death, and the uncertainty of its com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <hi>[animam velutmanibus geſtare, ut Domino ad nutum offeramus]</hi> ſo to carry our ſoules in our hands, that we be ready, willingly and preparedly to yeeld them up unto the Lord, let him call for them ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo ſuddenly. And, here bethinking my ſelfe both of the miſery and careleſneſſe of our times, I am loſt in the compariſon. If ever <hi>England</hi> were inhabited by people of <hi>Laiſh,</hi> if ever we were loſt in a Leathar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, buried in ſecurity, dull'd and deaded in a ſenſeleſſe courſe of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, then now eſpecially. What alatums and warnings have wee had, and even now are bellowing in our eares? and yet, <hi>Behold joy and gladneſſe, ſlaying of Oxen, and killing of ſheepe, eating of fleſh, and drinking wine</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.</note>] At ſuch a careleſneſſe the Prophet ſtands amazed, even when judgement was threatned, and for it the Lord aſſures the Jewes that they ſhould be utterly deſtroyed, <hi>[this iniquity ſhould not be purged away untill you die, verſe</hi> 14.] Oh my Brethren, how juſtly
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53814:8"/>may we be loſt then with the apprehenſion of the deadnes, &amp; ſenſeleſſe ſtupidity of our times? and what a fearfull and utter deſtruction may we expect at Gods hands, whoſe judgements are not onely threatned, but in execution? Oh! they fall thicke and heavy on us, and yet are we ſtill the ſame conſtant and careleſſe trudgers on in the old ſinnes of our nature, cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ome and crimes: nay, we hate to bee reformed, accounting thoſe our enemies and miſuſers, who would recall and better us. Warre, Civill warre (the moſt bloody and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of any) and the ſickneſſe rage amongſt us: the ſad breach be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the King and his great Councell, not made onely, but proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, the gappe growes daily wider, the Drumme ſpeakes louder, and the ſword drinkes blood thirſtier then ever, maſſacres, burnings, batteries, beſieges, (things not heard of for many, (many yeares in our Iſland) are our familiar miſery, and diſcourſe: yet (alas, alas!) as if we could neither ſee, nor heare, we continue the ſame careleſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>We often heare and reade of the cruell ſuffering of our Brethren, both with us and beyond the Seas, eſpecially in bleeding and dying <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſuch ſufferings that 'twould make the heart ake to thinke of them, the eare tingle to heare them, and the tongue faulter to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late them? and yet (ſtill tooke with the ſinnes and courſes of the world, with the vanities, idolatries, and ſuperſtitions of paſtimes) you never ſet about the making up of your accounts betweene God and your ſoules, of the making even with heaven; the Lord knowes how ſoone (ſooner 'tis to be feared then the Devill will let us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve) we may be made to drinke the dregs of that cup, which our poore Brethren have begun unto us.</p>
            <p>'Tis much to be wondred at, that you, which have ſo many argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for praying againſt ſudden death, ſhould make ſuch no-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration againſt it,. But doe you know what in that ſhort ejaculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you pray for? In it you doe not ſo much pray againſt theeves, bloody perſecuters, the Peſtilence, Impoſtumes, Apoplexies, Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, Fire, Water, Thunder, Earthquakes, the hazzards and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of Civill Warre onely, the uſuall meſſengers of untimely deathes: but that you may by a bleſſed uſe of the meanes (ſuch as praying, hearing, meditation, conference, ſanctified afflictions, &amp;c.) ſo confirme your faith, and perfect your repentance, that you may at all times be armed and provided againſt death: which meanes if you neglect, you live contrary to your owne pretended deſire, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53814:8"/>conſequently your prayer is vaine, and hypocriticall, an abomination to the Lord. But if your prayer be hearty, and your endevours anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, that thereby you are prepared to meet the Lord, whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he ſhall call for you, death then can never be ſudden, let it come when it will, and how it will, or by whom it will. So much truth hath that of <hi>Solomons</hi> in it, <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Wiſd</hi> 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>Though the righteous be prevented with death, yet ſhall he be at reſt,</hi>) though he be tooke away ſooner, then after the ordinary courſe of nature he might expect, in his youth (,hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily) full ſtrength, or beſt complexion, yet being tooke ſo doing, ſtanding on his watch, and guard, by faith and repentance having made Chriſt his, and by a continuall circumſpection living in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant expectation of death, he dyes in full aſſurance of reſt and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe: whereas wicked <note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. <hi>55.</hi> vit.</note> 
               <hi>bloody and deceitfull men ſhall not live out halfe their dayes i,</hi> either as a judgement on their hard hearts, which cannot repent, they ſhall be cut off in the midſt of their ſtrength and ſinnes, (as moſt interpret the words) or wicked men, though they die feeble, and aged, yet are they ſaid <hi>[dies dimidiare]</hi> not to live out halfe their dayes: becauſe they are ſo deeply in love with the world, and greedy of life, that they would willingly live as long againe, as already they had: or laſtly, are ſo careleſſe of their wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, ſo little knowing how the precious time paſſes away, that they are at their journeyes end, ere they thinke they have gone halfe way: thus being tooke away before they expected death, they are tooke away alſo ere they could halfe provide for it.</p>
            <p>Whereas if wee conſider how fraile and brittle even naturally, how ſubject to variety of caſualties, the frequent inſtruments of ſudden death, wee are; how many continually fall on every ſide of us; what ſtore of blood-thirſty Papiſts, and deſperate Libertines rage, and ſwarme in our land, each whereof <hi>[ſuae vitae in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curioſus, tuae dominus]</hi> growne careleſſe of his owne life, becomes maſter of thine; and upon theſe conſiderations alwayes keep <note n="e" place="margin">Sen. Ep. <hi>66.</hi>
               </note> in our view and minde, approaching death, we ſhould never be unprepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for it. <hi>Non ſubito moriuntur, qui ſemper ſe morituros cogitaverunt.] i.e.</hi> thoſe which with Saint <hi>Paul, dye daily</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.31.</note> (for ſo alſo may he be underſtood) cannot die ſuddenly. If therefore thou art reſolv'd to pray, <hi>From ſudden death good Lord deliver us,</hi> pray alſo with <hi>David</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92.12</note> 
               <hi>Teach us ſo to number our dayes that we may apply our hearts unto wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> i.e. bring them to wiſdome, make them wiſe: Now <hi>a wiſe mans heart</hi> (ſaith the Preacher <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.5.</note>) <hi>diſcerneth both time and judgement;</hi> the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53814:9"/>laſt time death, and the laſt judgement at Chriſts ſecond comming: not that he punctually knowes the time when he ſhall die, or when Chriſt ſhall in flaming fire be revealed from heaven; no, theſe times and ſeaſons belong unto God alone; but that he ſo well diſcernes the one and the other, that neither of them ſhall take him unprovided, to this purpoſe (as it becommeth a wiſe ſonne) [<hi>he gathereth in ſummer</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.5.</note>] In the long dayes of peace, and the glorious ſun-ſhine of the Goſpel, he layes up againſt Winter, <hi>i.e.</hi> either againſt times of blindneſſe and perſecution, when the meanes ſhall be denyed him, or elſe againſt death, when his ſtrength, like that of Plants, returnes to the earth, there to be kept untill the Reſurrections ſpring. You therefore which deſire to be freed from ſudden death, and by your prayer will witneſſe this your deſire, witneſſe it alſo, I beſeech you, by your carefull endeavour to prepare for its comming: pray that you may apply your hearts unto wiſdome, and manifeſt your ſelves to be wiſe ſonnes by gathering in Summer. O gather therefore (gather apace) whilſt it may be (yet) ſaid to be Summer: For ought I know, our Sunne may be declining, and our Summer drawing towards an end, darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſpirituall blindneſſe may be comming faſter on us, then the yeares Winter. We have (truth is) at this time a great ſhine, great ſtore of excellent and faithfull Preachers, but this may be but <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltimus lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernaefulgor,</hi> the laſt blaze of a dying candle, greateſt at laſt. The times are dangerous, full of teares and diſmall expectations (what bloody and deſperate deſignes are continually hatcht and diſcovered!) ſtrange talke and projects abroad, (God knowes whether the Jeſuites many yeares plot may now have iſſue) the ſcales may turn; (ſure I am our ſinnes and hardened hearts deſerve it) nay, doe we not ſee them ſwagge, and much adoe to keepe even? and did not the prayers and humiliations of ſome few good ſoules amongſt us, which ſigh and cry both for their owne, and the abominations of the land, adde weight unto the right ſcale, we were utterly loſt. O how ſuddenly may the freedome and liberty of injoying God in his Ordinances, for want of valuing and rightly uſing them, be tooke from us! Let there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, and me, and him, let every one of us reſolve with his Saviour, [<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.40.</note> 
               <hi>To worke the workes of him that ſent us, whilſt 'tis day, becauſe the night comes, when no man can worke;</hi>] <hi>the workes of him that ſent mee,</hi> not of my Father, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t obligationem faciendi ipſo miſſionis nomine decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Maldon. in locum.</note>, that he might ſhew the neceſſity of performing theſe workes, from his purpoſely being ſent for their performance. So ought wee
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53814:9"/>whilſt 'tis called to day, the time of our life, the time of our liberty, or the time allowed us for comming in, let us ply the buſineſſes breeding faith, and perfecting repentance, not onely becauſe they are the works of our Father, works tending to his glory, but alſo becauſe they are the works of him that ſent us: to this end hath hee ſent us into the World that we might repent and beleeve. It concernes us therefore carefully to uſe all the meanes to attaine to this perfection ere we are took out of the world, ere the night of death come on us, when no man can work.</p>
            <p>And for ought I know to the contrary, this night wherein no man can work, may as well include our laſt ſickneſſe, the time of dying, as that after it. Death is a harder task, and there is more to do in it then moſt men think of. How much buſineſſe we may then have, and how little time allowed for its diſpatch, God onely knowes. A careleſſe man going on in the ſinnes and courſes of the world, who thinkes it not worth the while in times of health and content, to trouble him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with the melancholy of repentance, will finde it employment more then enough on his death-bed for his weak heart and giddy head to ſet his houſe in order, (the chief thing in theſe troubles cared for by worldly <hi>Achitophels</hi>) with patience to undergoe his preſent paines, or to make the little and ſpiritleſſe fleſh, God ſhall leave him, willing to depart: What no time then (my brethren) and quiet will he have to make even with God, having run on 30, 40, 50. or more yeares in horrible arrerages? what little leiſure then will hee have to reſiſt the Devill, quiet his conſcience, or anſwer his clamorous ſinnes? I ſhall in a word ſhew you what a toile, and trouble, almoſt invincible, 'twill be for that man to dye well that hath lived ill, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting you with theſe 2. things;
<list>
                  <item>1. How hard it is for ſuch a one to be willing to dye.</item>
                  <item>2. How hard it is for him dying to reſiſt the Devill.</item>
               </list> Firſt, ſee how hard it will bee for him to bee willing to dye.</p>
            <p>Whatſoever is deſtructive to being or life, nature abhorres, the continuance and preſervation of this, being its onely appetite. Such a one then, as yet being in the ſtate of nature, cannot but mightily dread death. Nay, there hath been in the deareſt of Gods children this unwillingneſſe to dye; in <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> 
               <note n="(i)" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</hi> 37.20.</note> 
               <hi>Therefore heare me now I pray thee, and let my ſupplications be acceptable unto the King, my Lord, that thou cauſe me not to return to the houſe of Ionathan the Scribe, leſt I dye there.</hi> Our Saviour foretelling <hi>Peter</hi> that bold profeſſor, [<hi>Though
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53814:10"/>all ſhould be offended, yet not I</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.37.</note>] of his death, foretold him alſo how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly he would undergoe it, <hi>Thou ſhalt be carried whither thou wouldeſt not</hi> 
               <note n="(l)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 21.18.</note> And thus unwilling have the Saints been to dye, not only when wealth and pleaſures would have made them in love with life, but even in ſuch times as theſe, when ſinne and miſery did abound in the world; yet even then loath have they been to be took out of it: juſt as <hi>Lot,</hi> who though <hi>his righteous ſoule was vext day by day whilſt he lived in Sodom</hi> 
               <note n="(m)" place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.8.</note>, although he knew that a fearefull deſtruction was falling on it ſuddenly, yet how ſtrangely did he linger when God would take him out of it? inſomuch that the two Angels were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, laying their hands on him, to force him out. So weak was the pureſt and beſt fleſh that was ever made, even our Saviours, though united to the God-head, that it begged, <hi>If it be poſſible let this cup paſſe from me, Ipſa vox non exauditi magna eſt expoſitio Sacramenti,</hi> 
               <note n="(n)" place="margin">Leo in Mat. <hi>26.39.</hi>
               </note> The myſtery that Chriſt ſhould be God, and not be heard, is to tell us, that nature, fleſh and blood would not willingly purchaſe any good thing at ſo deare a rate as the price of its life, and being: Man then, yes the beſt man, nay God himſelfe, as he was a man, being not able without ſome ſtruggle and reluctancie to undergoe the laſt and ſad departure of the ſoule from the body (theſe deare, intimate and ancient friends:) with what heart-breaking then and tormenting unwillingneſſe doth a man formerly careleſſe and cuſtomary in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion yeeld up his ſoule?</p>
            <p>Againe, take notice how hard 'twill be for him to reſiſt the Devill, who then eſpecially recollects what malice and poyſon is within him, and vents it with moſt violence? <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltimum magno ſcelus animo pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trandum</hi> (as <hi>Medea</hi> of her ſelfe <note n="(o)" place="margin">Sen. Med.</note> Sad and preſent experience will tell you that when the beſiegers of a Town heare that the ſiege is ſhortly to be raiſed by the reliefe of approaching ſuccours, whereby it muſt neceſſarily be for ever reſcued out of their hands; how faſt and lowd will the Ordnance then thunder? what underminings, what ſtratagems, what force will be then uſed? then will they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collect whatſoever is man in them; not a brain, heart, or hand which ſhall not be then imployed, that their former hopes may not faile, or their former labour be loſt. And can the Devill (thinke you) who hath beſieged a ſoule for 30, 40, 50, or 60. yeares, and all this while hath more then hopes of taking it, be forced to remove ſiege ere hee hath tryed his utmoſt ſtrength, fury, and policie? And as the Devill will on our death-beds uſe his utmoſt endeavours; ſo ſhall we (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53814:10"/>careleſſe) be utterly diſenabled for reſiſtance, Alas! we have not in time of health got unto our ſelves the whole armour of a Chriſtian, which is very improbable, I will not ſay impoſſible, to begain'd in the laſt ſickneſſe; for the armour, the chiefeſt whereof is the ſhield of Faith, <hi>comes by hearing</hi> 
               <note n="(p)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.17.</note> God therefore ſeldome, very ſeldome beſtowes his graces on thoſe who in their health have not thrived by this Ordinance. And this is the reaſon why many careleſſe ones dye either without a Miniſter, or happily having an ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant looſe one, which knows not how to awaken a ſoule out of its damnable lethargy; or laſtly, having a faithfull one cannot by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their preſent paines or feare of hell, reape any profit by him; and if any ſeemingly to us are by Gods bleſſing on a faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter brought to repent, their repentance is ſcarce acceptable, or ſound; 1. Not acceptable. May not God ſay to ſuch, as he in the Comedy, <hi>[Cum nemini obtrudipoteſt, itur ad me,]</hi> you make me your refuge, not your choiſe; nay, you come not onely laſt unto me, but you reſerve that which is worſt for me: As in a barrell long drawn, <hi>[Non tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum minimum, ſed &amp; peſſimum relictum,]</hi> what is left is not onely lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, but grownes and dregges, the worſt of all; ſo offering your ſelves unto me on your death-beds, you give me onely that little of your life that is left, and this little is the worſt part too, made up of paines, weakneſſes, feares, and agonies; nor this neither would you give me, knew you how otherwiſe to beſtow it. What thank-worthy is it to be willing to leave your ſinnes, when you can keep them no longer? to renounce the world and its vanities, when you muſt be took from them? to give means to the poore, when you your ſelves cannot make uſe of them? to forgive your enemies, when you are diſinabled to return their injuries? or to perſwade your wife and children to rely on my providence, becauſe you can no longer lay up for them? 2. 'Tis uſually unſound. Many at their laſt gaſpe with teares in their eyes, groanes in their hearts, and confeſſion in their mouthes miſcarry and goe to hell, which we aſſuredly conclude to be in heaven, and have oft with joy related what good ends they have made, looking onely at their laſt penſiveneſſe, and not at their former lives, by which onely may we gueſſe what followes death, death being the Eccho to life, ſo we uſually dye as we live. This ſad truth my own reaſon and experience makes good. Some have I known in extremity of ſicknes, being as they thought the laſt, have made large confeſſions of their paſt errours, and have profeſt ſtrong reſolutions of amendment for
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53814:11"/>the future, in ſuppoſition of recovery. Oh! ſaid they, if it would pleaſe God to ſpare me, ſuffer me to recover my ſtrengh ere I goe hence, adde unto my yeares, mightily would I manifeſt, how the Lord hath ſanctified his viſitation unto me, by a reclaimed, ſtrict, and exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary life: yet being reſtored againe to their former ſtrength and liberty, (Dogges and Sowes as they are) have ſuddenly returned to their vomit and mire; this my experience tels me: now my reaſon tels me, that had theſe wretches died in this their repentance, which the devill made them beleeve, and they us was ſound and true, they muſt neceſſarily have gone to hell, becauſe their after relapſes, and wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowings proved them to be counterfeits.</p>
            <p>Thus are we neceſſitated to fear the miſcarrying of all theſe careleſs ones, though they are permitted to dye in their beds with a long and ordinary ſickneſſe Oh then in what danger do they live? and how do they walke upon the brinke of hell, which care not through repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and humiliation to make their peace with God in theſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall, bloody, dying times of ours, when probably this benefit of dying by a long ſickneſſe in the bed, being denyed them, they may be ſuddenly cut off with a head full of Wine, hands full of oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, eyes full of uncleanneſſe, and a heart full of malice; and thinke (Oh thinke) what then!</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> I know the jolly cuſtomary ſinners ordinary objection, (no great deciſion, ſure I am, no diſprofit to anſwer it) Though we as yet take our ſwing in the wayes and courſes of the world, and death may overtake us ere we are prepared for it; yet God can make us doe much in a little time, and that as much in as little time too, as the thiefe on the Croſſe did.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> 'Tis truth, to God nothing is impoſſible, much leſſe can any thing bee hard to him, yet know, that the LORD is infinitely juſt, as well as omnipotent, and I know not how it can ſtand with his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite juſtice miraculouſly to worke faith and repentance in a man on his death-bed, diſtracted with ſickneſſe, weeping friends, a clamorous conſcience, and a miſgiving heart, which in time of ſtrength and quiet, wilfully did ſhut his eyes againſt light, counted the preaching of the Word fooliſhneſſe, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.19.</note> 
               <hi>by which fooliſhneſſe,</hi> as hee and ſuch like count it, <hi>it pleaſeth God to ſave them that beleeve;</hi> he hath appointed as a meanes to worke faith in them whom he intends to ſave.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Rep. </seg>
               </label> But did he not make the thiefe on the Croſſe much repent and beleeve in a little time? and why may he not take the ſame courſe with me too?</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:53814:11"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſol. </seg>
               </label> This Example of the Thiefe onely proves, that if thou doeſt as truely repent, and beleeve on thy death-bed, as the Thief did on the Croſſe, though thou haſt beene formerly never ſo deſperately wilde and careleſſe, and canſt manifeſt the truth of thy faith and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance by as lively fruits as he did, thou art call'd, though at the laſt houre, and art aſſured of heaven: but it does not prove that God chooſeth the laſt houre to call ſoules in; though faith and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, be it given when it will, cannot miſſe of heaven: yet ſeldome or never, never but once, have we read or heard of, God beſtowes theſe graces on them, which till then never thought them worthy the ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The Fathers and moderne Divines afford ſtore of anſwers to this careleſſe Objection. Firſt, that of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is very good, <hi>Verum quidem dicis, quod Dous poenitentiae tuae indulgentiam promiſit, ſed huic dilaetioni tuae diem craſtinum non promiſit;</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Aug. de verb. Dom. Serm. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note>; That mercifull God which hath promiſed pardon upon repentance, hath not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to morrow to him that deferres it. Whenſoever therefore thou art call'd, come, doe not deferre thy comming till the eleventh houre, becauſe you have heard of the Thiefe then call'd: 'tis very like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in theſe bleeding, dying times, that thou ſhalt not live to the ſixth. Secondly, <note n="t" place="margin">Bolton Comfort. Walk.</note> from the Creation to this preſent houre, we have read but of one ſo miraculouſly ſnatcht out of the fire: 'twas a miracle where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God honoured the paſſion of his Sonne, and we may then onely looke for the like miracle, when Chriſt is againe to ſuffer. Thirdly, and laſtly, <note n="u" place="margin">Down. Warf. part. <hi>1.</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>32.</hi>
               </note> Princes now and then, though very ſeldome, as tokens of their clemency, pardon ſome man at the blocke, yet if any ſhall in hope hereof wilfully offend, and having offended, delay ſuing for a pardon, till he be led forth to execution, certainly he richly deſerves to ſuffer, not onely for his offence, but for his preſumption: juſt ſo the Lord to manifeſt the riches of his mercy, pardoned the thiefe, when death (death eternall) was ſeizing on him: now thoſe which hereupon ſhall take occaſion by continuing in their old and ſinfull courſes, fearefully to diſpleaſe his Majeſtie, or having fearfully offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, yet ſhall deferre by faith and repentance to ſue for pardon, ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly unworthy are they of grace and mercy, and as probably as deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly ſhall periſh in their ſinnes, and be delivered up to the blacke tormentor.</p>
            <p>To conclude therefore this firſt application (the ſutableneſſe whereof both to our times and ſad occaſion hath lengthened it a great deale beyond my intention) conſidering how hard, almoſt impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53814:12"/>it is to repent in our laſt ſickneſſe, and how probable it is that the laſt and uſuall leiſure of a long ſickneſſe, will by reaſon of our natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall frailties, the raging of infectious and violent diſeaſes, together with the thouſand caſualties of a bloody Civill warre, be utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed us, Let us ſpeedily ſet about working forth our ſalvation with feare and trembling: Let's forthwith endeavour to make our calling and election ſure: Now, now, in this breathing time of health and liberty, let's make good our title to heaven, confirm our evidence, our <hi>Faith, which is the evidence of things not ſeen,</hi> 
               <note n="(u)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1.</note> and have in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe our witneſſe, which is a good conſcience. The Scripture will not give you any incouragement or allowance for the leaſt delay. 'Tis <hi>to day if you wilt heare his voyce, harden not your hearts,</hi> 
               <note n="(w)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.7, 8.</note> not to morrow, if you will heare it; a dayes procraſtination doth harden the heart. Tis now is, not hereafter will be, the acceptable time: <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold now is the day of ſalvation,</hi> 
               <note n="(x)" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2.</note> The glorious time of the Goſpel, wherein peace and reconciliation through Chriſt is tendered on con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of faith and repentance, is expreſt by the preſent time and this day, to tell us (as I conceive) that there is a certain time allowed for every man to come in, which nick and opportunity, through a deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate careleſneſſe o'reſlipping, he is irrecoverably loſt. And therefore ought we to make ſo thrifty a uſe of this day, nay of this preſent time, of this preſent houre of my diſcourſe, as though this glaſſe were now turn'd up upon you, and that the time allotted for your, and your comming in did expire with the falling of the laſt ſand. For therefore (faith a Father <note n="(y)" place="margin">Auſtin.</note> is our laſt day conceald from us, that we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve every day to be the laſt. Oh that the Lord would make me a bleſſed inſtrument to move, melt, and ſoften but one heart here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, with the apprehenſion of that horrour and trembling, which ſeizes a foule impenitent and unprovided ſinner ſuddenly death-ſtrucken, and with the blow having his conſcience awakened; or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to what everlaſting burnings and torments he ſinks being never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened. But I have already treſpaſſed too much in the lengh of the uſe of the firſt branch. I ſhall recompence your patience in the ſhortneſſe of the other uſes. I goe forwards therefore to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond branch.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Branch </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Of what doſt thou boaſt thy ſelfe? i. e.</hi> what haſt thou which might be a juſt ſubject for boaſting? whatſoever thou dareſt own, or call thine, are either the good things of thy body, fortune, or thy mind, (as they are commonly diſtinguiſhed) we will make our examination ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53814:12"/>Firſt then, the good things of thy body are either beautie or ſtrength; but neither of theſe can juſtifie the leaſt pride or vaunt: Not beauty, which is <hi>Flos floris,</hi> the flower of a flower: Man at the beſt is but a Flower ſuddenly gone, <note n="(z)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 103.15.16.</note> 
               <hi>As for man his dayes are as graſſe, as a Flower of the field ſo he flouriſheth, for the wind paſſeth over it, and ſo it is gone, and the place thereof ſhall know it no more;</hi> but beauty is that which ſooneſt fades and alters in man, nay 'tis only <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note n="(*)" place="margin">ſch Aen.</note> the flower of colour, or the colour of a flower, which ſooneſt fades in a flower. Adde to this, that Scripture, experience, Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and moſt Hiſtories tell us, that thoſe ſinnes and miſeries can ſcarce be equalled, which this fond thing (we call beauty) hath produced. And even this might take off from boaſting of it, becauſe 'tis (as <hi>Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darus</hi> termes it) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the wanton Goddeſſes Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour. Nor can ſtrength, health, or manhood juſtifie thy boaſt; for know, eſpecially in the times of warre and ſickneſſe know, that the healthieſt, ableſt men fall thickeſt: Strong and able men are daily call'd to the dangers and hazzards of the warre, and the pureſt and beſt complexions ſooneſt yeeld to the infection and cruelty of raging diſeaſes; and moſt Phyſicians affirm, that <hi>Temperamentum ad pondus</hi> (as they call it) the exacteſt conſtitution hath moſt danger in it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it cannot long conſiſt in its perfection and excellencie: <hi>Et quia non poteſt in melius progredi, labitur in deterius,</hi> (as <hi>Galen</hi> ſomewhere) becauſe it cannot grow better, growes worſe: And that Aphoriſme of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> 
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Hippoc. ſect. <hi>2.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor. <hi>30.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> will hinder your boaſting, paines and diſeaſes are ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieſt in youth and age, [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,] of more force againſt the ſtrongeſt complexion. A ſudden tempeſtuous ſickneſſe, a feaver, the Stone, or wind in the Stomack (as a tempeſt deales with ſturdy Okes) ſooneſt plucks up and overturnes the ſtrongeſt, when weak creeping wretches come off eaſier.</p>
            <p>And if thou haſt no juſt cauſe to boaſt of the good things of thy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, much leſſe cauſe haſt thou to boaſt of the things we call the good things of Fortune, becauſe they are leſſe thine own, longer winged, and flye away ſooner. Firſt, no cauſe haſt thou to boaſt of thy riches, for <hi>nec verae ſunt, nec tuae</hi> 
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Bern. Ser. <hi>49.</hi>
               </note>, they are neither truly wealth, nor thine owne: ſo farre are they from being thine owne, that we are forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to gather them for our ſelves. <hi>Lay not up</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>for your ſelves treaſures upon earth</hi> (not that we are forbidden with honeſt and moderate carefulneſſe to endeavour an increaſe of our ſtock and talent: <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.19.</note> No, <hi>the hand of the diligent maketh rich,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> 
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.9.</note>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:53814:13"/>their growing rich is made the reward and encouragement to mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and honeſt carefulneſſe; but that we ſhould not lay up treaſures for ourſelves; that we ſhould not therfore carke, ſpare, and pine, that we may purchaſe a propriety in wealth, that we may have heapes of gold and ſtore of lands that we may call our owne, that we may have what to ſet our hearts on with that foole in the Goſpell ſinging lullabie to our ſoules, <hi>Soule take thy reſt, thou hast much goods laid up for many yeeres,</hi> 
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 12.19.</note> thou haſt goods laid up, the goods are thine, and for thee onely are they laid up: Well might this foole by the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt <note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39 6.</note> be ſaid to <hi>be diſquieted in vaine, becauſe he ſtored up riches, and knowes not who ſhall enjoy them:</hi> So farre is he from knowing who ſhall enjoy them, that he knowes not for whom he gathers them. Even in this ſenſe alſo that charge of the Apoſtle <note n="(g)" place="margin">I <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.24.</note> requires obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>Let no man ſeek his owne, but every one anothers wealth,</hi> Let him not ſeek wealth for himſelfe to make it his owne, but for others, either for his children, friends, Common-wealth, eſpecially for God, for the upholding of his cauſe, or the reliefe of his ſervants. And oh that men would conſider what no propriety, what no right they themſelves have to their wealth, what no maſters themſelves are of their owne purſe, when Gods cauſe calls for't, and bids them deliver!</p>
            <p>Again, the deceitfulneſſe of riches (as our Saviour calls it<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 4.19.</note> which eſpecially failes us in our greateſt neceſſity, ſhould keep us from boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of them; when age or ſickneſſe throwes thee on thy death-bed, thy full barnes and cram'd bagges will afford thee little comfort, thy corn will not then be nouriſhing, nor thy gold reſtorative. In this needfull time they deale with us as <hi>Hagar</hi> did with <hi>Iſhmael</hi> 
               <note n="(i)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 23.16.</note>, being not able then to comfort us with the waters of refreſhment, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from us, they yeeld us up unto death; and after death thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort will be leaſt of all, thine I mean, which prideſt thy ſelfe in thy wealth: for in that laſt and great day they will but encreaſe thy <hi>onus,</hi> adde to the ſcore, and make thy accompts deeper and more intricate. This miſery riches bring with them though well got, but if ill got, got by oppreſſion, the trade of Vſury, or other unlawfull gaines, what no cauſe haſt thou to boaſt of them? eſpecially in thy laſt ſickneſſe, when their deceivableneſſe plainly appeares: this heavie ſtrait wilt thou be brought to, if thou make reſtitution, as God and thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence requires, thou muſt then leave thy children beggers; if not, thy ſoule ſinks into hell: <hi>Coelum undique, &amp; undique pontus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, no juſt cauſe haſt thou to boaſt of thy honours, which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53814:13"/>though in themſelves good, not onely as they are Gods gifts: [<hi>He it is that raiſeth the poore out of the duſt, and lifteth the begger from the dunghill, to ſet them amongst Princes, and to make them inherit the ſeat of glory</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.8.</note>] but alſo as they are rewards to thoſe that ſtick for his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour [<hi>He will honour thoſe that honour him</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30.</note>]. Yet to thoſe that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to pride themſelves in them are juſt cauſe of dread and ſhame, for theſe reaſons: Firſt, ſuch will deſire honour farre above their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert and place: Thus <hi>Alexander,</hi> who gloried much in his height and Victories, willingly accepted of divine reſpect; when ſome of his baſe Courtiers perſwaded him he was a God, then preſently became he violent againſt the few faithfull friends of his that gaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayed it, ſo violent, that the faithfulleſt of them was murthered; and no wonder, for thinking himſelf a god, 'twas eaſie for him afterwards to conceive that he was not bounded by Law or duty. Secondly, ſuch will not ouely affect honour farre above them, but whatſoever ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour they affect, they are eager in the purſuit of it, and it cannot ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be gueſt, what variety of ſinnes and dangers ſuch will run tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row to ſatisfie their luſt; they care not how diſhoneſt the meanes be, how baſe the inſtruments, nor how foule the way, ſo they may get to their journeys end. God grant that we owe not our preſent ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, nay our preſent ſinnes, our hideous lyings, oathes, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, bloody ſtratagems, murthers, and oppreſſions to ſuch inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate deſires. Thirdly and laſtly, they which deſire honour meerly that they may vaunt and gliſter, they will not deſire that which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God nor man hath thought fit for them, and with a ſtrange ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerneſſe, and hazard purſue this deſire, untill they have either loſt themſelves or gain'd their unjuſt honour, but into theſe ſtraights are they alſo caſt, <hi>viz.</hi> to be as baſe and ſinnefull in keeping their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as they were in the obtaining of it (according to that rule of the Hiſtorian <note n="m" place="margin">Saluſt.</note>, <hi>[Iiſdem artibus retinetur gloria, quibus parta fuit]</hi> glory is to be kept upon the ſame tearmes it was got; if thou by ſinnefull courſes and baſe inſtruments gotteſt up, the ſame finnefull courſes and baſe inſtruments are neceſſary to the keeping of thy height, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe they which ſet thee up will pull thee downe again, <hi>ex. gr.</hi> if by flattery and diſſembling thou gotteſt ſo high, then (O miſery!) muſt thou ſtill be baſe and flatter: if by bribing, then muſt thou ſtill be ſending and giving, otherwiſe 'twill bee with thee as with a Comet, which (ſay Aſtronomers) continues its blaze and luſtre no longer then it hath matter to feed and maintain it; nor will thy
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53814:14"/>glory, if thus come by, laſt longer then thou haſt oyle to foment it, baſe ſmooth language or gifts; but when theſe faile, thy great friend will begin to frown, and then down thou muſt, and wilt fall like a ſpent exhalation. Put theſe together then, and tell me. Have thoſe which are ſo unjuſt in their deſires, and ſo violent in the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit of them, ſo violent (I ſay) that they oft run through any ſin, and venture on any danger, rather then they'l be hindred, yes and are forced for the moſt part to a neceſſary continuance in the ſinnes, by which, and liableneſſe to thoſe dangers, through which they waded to their heigth: have theſe (I ſay) juſt cauſe of boaſting of their honour thus got and enjoyed? Alas! my brethren, did you feele and know the ſtings and burnings, the throwes and cuttings of their guilty conſciences, if they have any, you would not be long in giving in your anſwer. But one ſtep further, that they (Atheiſts as they are) have no conſciences, for none but Atheiſts would be ſo violent and ſinfull in the purſuit of honour, and that they can <hi>gloriam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſdem artibus retinere, quibus parta fuit,</hi> keep their heigth and glory with the ſame ſins and ſtrength wherewith 'twas got; yet all this will but make them great and glorious ſinners, whoſe end is horrour to imagine.</p>
            <p>And then for the beſt honours which are to be gained the beſt and moſt innocent way, though offered and forced on thee; labour thou maiſt indeed to deſerve them, but never to make them matter of thy boaſt: Hence our Saviour, the people crying, <hi>Bleſſed is he which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth King of Iſrael</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.38.40.</note>, would by no meanes be brought to rebuke them; but underſtanding their intention was to make him King, <hi>he withſtood them</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.</note>, whereupon <hi>Hilarius, [Inſinnat quod ſtatum regium, &amp; mundi honores volebat mereri, &amp; contemnere]</hi> he thereby willed the deſert, and contempt of worldly honours: <hi>Magne fortuna est magna ſervitus,</hi> high place is but an honourable ſervitude, and will ſtand in little ſtead at laſt: it cannot ſtave of deaths arreſt, though happily it may the Lawes; Even of the greateſt of mortal, ſaith the Pſalmiſt <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.4.</note>, <hi>his breath gooth forth, he returneth to his earth,</hi> (the earth from whence he came) <hi>and then all his thoughts</hi> (not good thoughts certainly, for ſuch are gloriouſly ſatisfied, but his bad thoughts, his thoughts of ſoaring, revenge, rioting, &amp;c.) <hi>ſhall periſh:</hi> Then (as <hi>Lucretius</hi> wittily <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Eripitur perſona, manet ves,</hi> the play will bee done, his <hi>exiit</hi> come, and his robes took off, he will appeare an arrant man, not of better earth or mould then the pooreſt begger.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:53814:14"/>
            <p>Thirdly and laſtly, no juſt cauſe haſt thou to boaſt of thy great friends, thy dependancy or mighty relations, and that for theſe reaſons; Firſt, becauſe moſt are falſe, they dive and winde themſelves into thy boſome; and being got into thy innermoſt cloſet, acquainted with thy naturall bent and inclination; they will accordingly ſo bende and crook their words and actions, and therewith as with a falſe key, they will unlock and open thy heart, that they may deale with thee as <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiaris</hi> in <hi>Tacitus</hi> did with <hi>Sabinus</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Annal.</hi> 1.4.</note>, ſound and pump thee untill they have got enough out of thee to undoe thee. They will <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 13.11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>ſmiling on thee get out thy ſecrets, lay up thy words, will not ſpare to doe thee hurt, or to put thee in priſon:</hi> There are I am confident plenty of ſuch friends ſtoring up againſt a black day. How uſuall a way of poyſoning is it to profeſſe Phyſick? Who would not have took <hi>Ioab</hi> to have been <hi>Amaſa's</hi> friend? ſee his friendly greeting, <hi>Art thou in health my brother?</hi> Takes him by the beard to kiſſe him, but nothing leſſe; this onely to make way for more ſurely murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him; for hereby (ſaith the Text) <hi>Amaſa took no heed to Ioabs ſword, ſo hee ſtrook him therewith on the fifth ribbe and ſhed out his bowels to the ground, and ſtrook him not againe</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.9.10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, ſuppoſe thy friends not ſuch wretched Caitiffs, as to intend to build themſelves a fortune out of thy ruines, or riſe the higher by treading on thee (though the diſcovery of many bloody underminings tell us, there are ſtore of ſuch amongſt us) notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding few are there which doe truly intend the good of their friends. Many will be friends to thy wealth, thy power, wiſedome, or hoſpitality, which will not be ſo to thee; ſuch as the Philoſopher ſayes, <hi>[qui eo uſque oleum infundunt, donec lucernâ opus est]</hi> which put oile into the Lamp no longer, then they make uſe of its light: But <hi>when thy candle is put out,</hi> as <hi>Iob</hi> phraſes it <note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 18.6</note>, when thou art diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enabled from affording them comfort and reliefe, then preſently will they fall off, and (as he complaines of his friends <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 6.15.</note>) <hi>deale deceitfully with thee as a brook,</hi> in ſummer, in the heat of thy afflictions, when thou haſt moſt need of them, faile thee, and like <hi>Davids</hi> kinsfolk ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farre of <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, grant thy friend true, and for the time faſt, yet how ſoone may another creep into his boſome, and thruſt thee out? I need not to goe ſo farre back as to tell you that <hi>Haman</hi> (but now <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> his great Favorite, the onely man privy to his ſports, and buſineſſes) was on a ſudden forc't to be an inſtrument of <hi>Mordecai's</hi> honour,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53814:15"/>whom ere-while hee would not ſuffer to ſit covered before him, and immediately afterwards hang'd on that Gallowes he rear'd for him <note n="z" place="margin">Eſt. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> How ſuddenly the ſcales have turn'd, and good carding altered, our own Chronicles will tell you, yes, our own times (very late times) will tell you how a long impriſoned perſon hath been took out of the priſon, judged, and cenſured his but now mighty adverſary: 'Twere loſſe of time to ſhew you thoſe many, whom ſympathy and converſation have been long a twiſting, which in a thrice have been as famous for thei enmity, as ever they were for their friendſhip. One inſtance ſhall ſerve, <hi>Sejanus</hi> had but now ſo much of the boſome of <hi>Tiberius</hi> (as the Hiſtorian tells us <note n="(a)" place="margin">Tacitus</note>, that he ſtiles him <hi>[conſors curarum,]</hi> partnet in his cares; and ſo much of his dignity, that he ſtiles him <hi>[Collega imperii]</hi> partner in his Empire: but how ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fatally did the Scene alter, next day, nay next houre <hi>[Calca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Caeſaris hoſtem;] Macro</hi> a new pellet, but his old Adverſary, thruſt him out of <hi>Tiberius</hi> his favour, brought men and Authority to the Senate to ſpoyle him of his life, and (which was worſe to an am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious man) of his honours too: then thoſe, which but this houre were his Idolaters, became with the hearing of ſix lines read, proud to bee his executioners, and made him the ſacrifice, which but this morning was their God.</p>
            <p>Fourthly and laſtly, ſuppoſe thy friend (thy greateſt friend) true and faſt, as conſtant too, as the three paires the Heathens boaſt of: let him be as cloſe and ſure to thee as <hi>Ionathan</hi> was to <hi>David;</hi> nay further, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him as cloſe and as faſt to his God too, yet he is ſtill but Gods inſtrument: if thou doſt ill, he neither will, nor dares ſtick to thee; if thou doſt well, yet can he be nor more nor longer thine, then God ſhall ſuffer him. Nay let me tell you, if high friends, great depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, or mighty relation be that which you pride your ſelves in and boaſt of, God may (and 'cis probable he will) ſo cruſh and humble thy great friend, that thou maiſt gladly make uſe of <hi>Peters [I know not the man:]</hi> 'twas I believe ſomewhat in the cauſe why the Lord leſus ſo left <hi>Peter,</hi> that he denied, forſwore, and wept, becauſe he relied too much upon the <hi>man Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> Reade we not that 'twas uſuall amongſt the antient to attach and accuſe friends as acceſſories, and conclude every traitours friend a conſpiratour? and that humour is not yet quite worn out: For though judgement doth not ſo peremptorily (as in old times) ſeize the friends of the accuſed, or guilty, yet ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſticks cloſe to them; and if jealous, ſuſpitious eyes are about thee,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53814:15"/>'tis as bad as moſſe about a tree; 'twill for the preſent hinder thee from thriving, and at laſt by degrees wither thee. No ſooner was our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our betraid, but preſent enquiry was made after his friends and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers; then preſently <hi>thou alſo Peter waſt with Ieſus of Galilee</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 26.69.71.</note> and again, <hi>this fellow alſo was with Ieſus of Nazareth: (b)</hi> And though the Diſciples fell not preſently with their Maſter, yet his cauſe was their death, and becauſe they perſecuted him, they perſecuted them much more.</p>
            <p>This have I ſaid, not that I would have you leave your Saviour, or feare to profeſſe friendſhip to his cauſe and ſervants, but then you might know that friendſhip, and relation only, be they never ſo inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, may cauſe your overthrow. Hence the <hi>Athenians Phocion</hi> asking them why others (he only being thought guilty) ſhould bee accuſed, anſwered onely <hi>[quod amici fuerint]</hi> becauſe they were his friends. Thus <hi>Alexander</hi> (as <hi>Curtius</hi> tels us) ſought the death of all <hi>Parmeno's</hi> friends and allies; and to <hi>Sejanus</hi> his friends <hi>[amicitia objecta eſt]</hi> they were accuſed of friendſhip: Nay (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth of him <note n="*" place="margin">Apoloz.</note>, <hi>[portati ſunt in carcerem emorituri puberes, qui mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem neſciebant, &amp; ſub cultro ridebant]</hi> 'twas ſufficient fault for his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to be his, who (tender wretches!) were put to death, ere they know what it meant, and ſported with that axe that was to end both their mirth and life: So ſuddenly may the wind turn and times change, that you may with a heavy heart ſay of your great friend, what <hi>Evodius</hi> does of <hi>Sejanus, [Aequè illum amaſſe quàm offendiſſe periculo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum]</hi> his friendſhip is now as dangerous as before his anger was.</p>
            <p>To put this together then, if ſome friends are baſely treacherous many ſelfe-ended, others inconſtant, and all but men fraile, and uncertaine in their perſons and condition, ſubject to the miſcarriages of ſtate and change of times; yes ſo ſubject, that thy former friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and relation with them may utterly ruine thee, though thou and thy great friend be never ſo innocent. This being ſo, doubtleſſe thou haſt no juſt cauſe to boaſt of thy friends, though I bate thee the ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it.</p>
            <p>But were we not eare and eye-witneſſes to the contrary, we could not think that any one which hath not left to bee man can be ſo very a craven as to crow on theſe dung-hills, boaſt of meere froth, of theſe low, wordly, gaudy nothings: a Heathen could ſay <note n="a" place="margin">Sen. prae. ſat in ratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. queſted.</note> 
               <hi>[quagrave;m contempta res eſt homo, ſi non ſupra humana ſo exercuirit!]</hi> man is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53814:16"/>a very inconſiderable thing if the things here below onely take up his time and thoughts: yet there are <hi>[bona animi]</hi> the good things of the mind, ſomethings within man, ſuch as knowledge, ſweet and affable diſpoſitions, morall vertues, together with reaſon, and other gifts, and naturall endowments, which a man may better call his owne, and therefore the Heathens have ſo ſtrangely boaſted of them, which ſome, even Chriſtians have thought may enable them <hi>[expu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris naturalibus]</hi> meerely of themſelves to lay hold and keepe faſt their Saviour, to worke out their ſalvation with feare and trembling (as pround nature miſconſtrues, that place of the Apoſtle;) and therefore ſome, even Chriſtians have boaſted of theſe naturall, and morall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments. But for my part ſo ſenſible am I (and the Lord continue me ſo) of theſe wretched fruits, which <hi>(radix iſta damnata</hi>) (as the Father cals her o) nature that da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>able root brings forth, <note n="b" place="margin">Auſtin. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. contia Iuian.</note> that I cannot but in reſpect of theſe good things of the mind alſo (as they are called) continue my wonder and queſtion, and aske the richeſt endowed, the compleateſſ man, that nature or induſtry hath made, Why boaſteſt thou thy ſelfe in theſe?</p>
            <p>And firſt, what juſt ſubject of boaſting can the wiſdome and knowledge of the experienteſt learnedſt man afford him, which ſome have thought at the beſt to be but opinion: that whatſoever we are capable of, is not onely uncertaine in its poſſeſſion, but in its knowledge alſo: nay, this Tenet of theirs, <hi>That nothing can be truely knowne,</hi> is not ſufficiently knowne unto themſelves: as <hi>Lucretius</hi> well;</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nil ſciri quiſquis putat, id quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> neſcit</l>
               <l>An ſciripoſſit, quod ſemel ſcire fatetur <note n="c" place="margin">Lib. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>But grant our knowledge may be ſure and certaine, yet what juſt matter of boaſting can that be, which is purchaſed with ſo much ado, and may be loſt ſo eaſily? How much money, travell, ſickneſſe, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ſtudy (though vulgar ignorance thinke otherwiſe) goe to the making of a wiſe knowing learned man, whom an Apoplexy, Lethargy, Palſie, or diſcontent, in a moment beſots, or ſtrikes luna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick? Thus <hi>Eccius, Luthers</hi> great adverſary (as great for his learning, as his malice, as <hi>Oſiander</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">In Epit: Cen. <hi>16. e.</hi> Com. lib. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> &amp; Cardinall <hi>Creſſentius,</hi> the Popes Nuntio, at the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> as <hi>Sleiden</hi> relates) were ſtrucke with a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den frenzie: and <hi>Calius Rhodiginus</hi> will tell you that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> the Fountaine and Conduit of almoſt all learning and wiſedome, was by a violent ſurpriſall of griefe ſuddenly cut off <note n="f" place="margin">Antiq. lect. l. <hi>29.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> The <hi>Stoi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es</hi> the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53814:16"/>the greateſt Idolaters that ever wiſedome and learning had, have ſet too low a rate upon them that they ſticke not to affirme that <hi>Hera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clitus</hi> and <hi>Pherecides</hi> (men oraculouſly wiſe amongſt them) would have changed their wiſedome for health, if thereby they might have beene ridde of their paines and Sickneſſe for health (a good ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to us and beaſts, that ſome have therefore preferr'd riches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Et divitem optare podagram</l>
               <l>Non dubitant— <note n="g" place="margin">Iuven, Satyr.</note>)</l>
            </q>
            <p>Thus many have there beene (and thrſe none of the weakeſt neither) that have preferr'd a childes ſimplicity, and a fooles ignorance before it, leſt by a fore-thought, and miſerably wiſe anticipation, they might ſuffer afflictions before they fall, and being fallen, adde to the load by a punctuall compariſon of paſt happineſſe and preſent miſery. Truely in this reſpect ſpake the Greeke Poet [Ev <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] the ſweeteſt life is in knowing nothing <note n="h" place="margin">Sophoc. Ajax.</note> of which <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> gives the reaſon; becauſe <hi>in much wiſdome is much ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Eccleſu.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And if thou haſt ſo little cauſe to boaſt of knowledge and wiſedome, then much leſſe cauſe haſt thou to boaſt of a towardly diſpoſition, naturall ingenuity, pleaſantneſſe of wit, yes or of the full chaine of morall vertues, which all put together, are but <hi>[ſemina &amp; radices prudentiae]</hi> but the rootes and ground-worke of wiſedome. Know therefore that in the ſecond place, ſweetneſſe and ingenuity of Nature, nor the greateſt ſtocke of morality, can juſtifie thy boaſt; (i meane ſtill, though we abſtract from boaſting its ſinfulneſſe) Though theſe happily are in themſelves good, Gods gifts, and chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge thy thankfulneſſe, yet not ſo abſolutely good, or thine owne, as to juſtifie a boaſt For theſe are at the beſt but home-made gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which may perchance ſerve to keepe out wet in the world, get name and repucation amongſt men, yet is it not a fit dreſſe for the Spouſe to meet her Bride-groome in: and if thou art not better clad at the great marriage-feaſt, thou wilt be found without thy wedding garment. Agains, doe not theſe endowments, if not ſeaſoned by the Holy Ghoſt, make us more yeelding and liable to temptation? witneſſe theſe common phraſes, which oft, out of a fond irreligious cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, we beſtow on ſwine, <hi>Alas! he is a man of a very good nature, An enemy onely to himſelfe, You ſee the worſt of him,</hi>) the worſt, quoth you! God forbid I ſhould ever ſee any of you ſo bad: for happily ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53814:17"/>and himſelfe, he never ſwore; cheated, lyed, quarrell'd. &amp;c. and may on the Lords day paſſe with moſt for a very good Chriſtian: but on Munday there comes a Meſſenger from the Devill, one of the drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king crew, has him abroad, where, after a Catowſe or two, hee lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth both his ſenſe and goodneſſe, and then his laſcivious geſture, and prophane language, confeſſe that his former acted civility was not grace, but ſome towardly ſeedes of morality, which vainglory and imitation had foſtered into a cuſtome. Yet this is not all, theſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally ſweet diſpoſitions and vertues make a man not onely more pliable to temptation, but (though I dare not ſay, as ſome, that they are at the beſt a hinderance to Religion) yet certainly may I ſay with a Divine of ours, if they are not rectified by the good Spirit, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but blocke up the way to the power of godlineſſe; and upon this his reaſon too: becauſe many, when they have perceived that naturall ſweetneſſe, and civill uprightneſſe have got them name and credit in the world, and that it will conſiſt with the profit and pleaſure which ſome boſome ſinne affords them, then preſently ſtop they here, conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelves with a probable being in the right way, when (to ſpeake truth) 'tis but a plauſible way to eternall death.</p>
            <p>And if the beſt of naturall diſpoſitions, nay, if the beſt of our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall habits which are [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] properly call'd vertues, are no juſt matter for boaſting, then certainly neither is our reaſon, or ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of judgement, which is onely [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] a naturall vertue, and improperly ſo call'd. Know <hi>Socinus</hi> in the third place, that thy reaſon, though naturally never ſo deepe or ſharpe, cannot make good thy pride and ſtrange boaſting of it: which by nature, and of it ſelfe is <hi>darkened,</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.18.</note> Nay, <hi>darkneſſe it ſelfe</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.8.</note>, and this is that <hi>darkneſſe which could not comprehend the light,</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Iohn 1.5</note> that <hi>veſſell which is not able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the way of the Higheſt</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">2 <hi>Fſdr.</hi> 4.11.</note> Though I cannot well ſide with them, who make reaſon an abſolute enemy to Religion, <note n="e" place="margin">Hook. Eccleſ. pol. l. <hi>3.</hi> Sect. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> and that the way to be ripe in faith, is to be raw in wit and judgement. Though there is on the other ſide, <hi>Sapientia Dei in aperto</hi> (as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes it) the wiſedome of God legible in the creature, though the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieſt Heathen hath a Law written in his heart ſufficient for convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet there is <hi>[ſapientia Dei in myſterio]</hi> the <hi>myſtery of godlineſſe, (as</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes) <note n="f" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6.</note> which is farre beyond the reach and ken of naturall reaſon: which when I faſten my thoughts on, I cannot but thinke and ſay, nay, [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] with the ancient Father, Shall I cry out [<note n="g" place="margin">Iuſtin. Mart de trinit. p. <hi>388.</hi>
               </note>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>]
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:53814:17"/>that theſe points of Chriſtianity are above our underſtanding, above our reaſon, and above the capacity of created nature, and therefore a little before he affirmeth, that the interpretation of them ought not to be [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] according to humane reaſon <note place="margin">P. 375.</note> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> but according to the ſenſe and will of the doctrine of the Spirit, eſpecially (ſaith hee) [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] with the ſonnes of the Church. Once therefore well ſpake. <hi>Tilenus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Syntag. l. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi> theſ. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> though ſince miſerably he fell <hi>(ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem extinguit fides ut ducem, &amp; dominam, adhibet ut pediſſequam)</hi> faith refuſeth reaſon, as judge or guide, but not as follower, or ſervant. Hence excellently Saint <hi>Auſtin, (Noli quarere intelligere ut credas, ſed crede ut intelligas)</hi> labour not to underſtand that thou mighteſt beleeve, but beleeve that thou mighteſt underſtand. This naturall reaſon of ours, if it hath any light, 'tis in it ſelfe no better in reſpect of the myſteries of godlineſſe, then that of an <hi>ignis fatuus,</hi> which miſerably miſleads: or at the beſt, it is but as a ſtarre to guide us (like that of the ſhepheards) to Chriſt: now as a ſtarre, the Sunne and Moone withholding their ſhine, yeelds no light or comfort: So if the Word of God, or the Spirit which enlightens the Word with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold their light, we ſhall, notwithſtanding the ſtrength of naturall reaſon, be enwrapped in perpeturall night: and (truth is) ſuch 2 ſtarre hath it proved to many in <hi>Polonia,</hi> and <hi>Racovia,</hi> even the ſtarre mentioned by Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> and called <hi>Wormewood, which made rivers ſo bitter, that men tasting of them dyed, dyed thereof.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>To goe forward then, if naturall reaſon (the richeſt jewell in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures Cabinet) is ſo blinde in matters of Religion, that it cannot make good a <hi>Socinian</hi> boaſt, we may juſtly goe further and conclude: that nature beſtowing her gifts with never ſo broad a hand, cannot afford her greateſt darling, matter ſufficient for one ſelfe-boaſt. Let me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the next place aske thee, Why doeſt thou boaſt thy ſelfe in any gifts, excellency, or ſtrength of Nature whatſoever? Is't not a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt vanity of the poore to boaſt of their wealth, the broken hearted of their jollity, the Captives of their liberty, the blinde of their quicke ſight, or a bruiſed Cripple of his legges? If ſo, what fond madneſſe is it for us to boaſt of our naturall abilities? For poore and blind Captives are we, bruiſed and broken Cripples by nature, and this we muſt know, and acknowledge too, ere we can reape any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit by Chriſts comming: Witneſſe that of the Prophet, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 61.1. <hi>Luke</hi> 4.18.</note> which our Saviour affirmes to be ſpoken of himſelfe; <hi>The Spirit of the Lord
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:53814:18"/>was upon him, to preach the Goſpel,</hi> but to whom? to <hi>the poore, (i.e.)</hi> thoſe which through the ſight and acknowledgment of their own naturall poverty were poore and low in their own thoughts; <hi>he ſent him to heale,</hi> but whom? the <hi>broken-hearted, (i.e.)</hi> thoſe whoſe hearts are almoſt broken with the diſcovery of their wretched eſtate, both by actuall tranſgreſſion and naturall pollution, <hi>to preach deliverance to the captives only,</hi> thoſe which ſeriouſly confeſſe, what ſlavery is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathed them from <hi>Adam</hi> to ſinne, and the Devill, <hi>recovery of ſight to the blinde, (i.e.)</hi> thoſe which are truly ſenſible of their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ignorance and adverneſſe unto ſaving truths, and <hi>to ſet at liberty thoſe which are bruiſed,</hi> which are ſufficiently ſenſible of that all-over bruiſe they had by their firſt Parents fall; he fell with us in his armes, we were equally crippled with him; but alas, this was not all, wee were not onely maimed in the fall, but ſtruck dead; <hi>for as in Adam all die, ſo in Christ ſhall all be made alive</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15 15.</note>; For ought I know to the contrary, the Apoſtle here excludes all theſe from having life in Chriſt, which will not acknowledge that by nature they are dead; and what reaſon think you, hath a dead man to boaſt of his naturall abilities? Be we adviſed rather by <hi>Proſper</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Lib. de libera arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trio ad Ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin.</note>, <hi>(agnoſcat ſe humana de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitas, &amp; cum mortui vivificantur, cum caeci illuminantur, impii juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficantur, confiteantur &amp; vitam, &amp; lumen, &amp; juſtitiam Ieſum Chriſtum)</hi> let humane weakneſſe acknowledge it ſelfe, and ſince the dead are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to life, the blind recover their ſight, and ſinners are juſtified, let them acknowledge that Chriſt above is their life, their light, and their righteouſneſſe; and (as the Father goes on) <hi>qui gloriatur, in Domino glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietur, qui cum eſſet impius, caecus, &amp; mortuus, à liberatore ſuo gratis accepit &amp; justitiam, &amp; lumen, &amp; vitam; he that doth glory, let him glory in the Lord</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10 17.</note>, not in himſelfe, who a ſinner, blind, and dead recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>gratis, (i.e.)</hi> without deſert preſent or fore-ſeen; of his Saviour light, life, and righteouſneſſe. I muſt wonder therefore that ſome like <hi>Philotas</hi> in <hi>Curtius</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Curt. l. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>(meruiſſe mortem conſiteri pudet,)</hi> ſcorne to acknowledge that even by nature they deſerve to die and (as there the Hiſtorian of him,) <hi>mallent injuriam accepiſſe quàm vitam;</hi> had rather die, and that for ever, ſo thereby God may be accuſed of injuſtice, then accept of ſalvation meerely through Chriſt. Theſe with <hi>Bona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Lib. quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to diſtinct. <hi>14.</hi> qu. <hi>2.</hi> ar.</note>, boaſt that <hi>(qui facit quod inſe eſt, cogitans bonitatem Dei &amp; juſtitiam, qui malum edit, &amp; revertentibus miſericors eſt,)</hi> he that does what he can, (as his diſciples have Engliſhed him) bethinking him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of the goodneſſe and juſtice of God, which hates iniquity and is
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53814:18"/>mercifull to penitents, and hereby begets feare in himſelfe from the thoughts of the juſtice of God, and hope of pardon from the thought of his mercy, who thus begins to think (ſayes he) and then <hi>(faciendo quod in ſe eſt)</hi> doing what he can, is of himſelfe diſpoſed for juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Thus our late pretending Defender of the Proteſtant Religion (who deſended our Religion, as the Colonell did Portſ-mouth, that it might be more aſſuredly yeelded up, undertook its defence him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to hinder others from more ſafely keeping of it,) thus may I ſay, this pretending Defender ſayes, men are to uſe their beſt endeavours, to believe the Scriptures in their true ſenſe, and to live according to it; this if they doe (as I hope many doe on all ſides) truly and ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is impoſſible but they ſhould believe aright <note n="b" place="margin">Chilling. Relig. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. anſiv. to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat. p. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note>, (it had been mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly ſpoken had he ſaid 'twas probable they ſhould believe, aright; ſo might he have meant, that this their honeſt care and endeavour is an argument that God intends good unto their ſoules; but to ſay it is impoſſible but they ſhould believe aright, makes this uſe of their beſt endeavours, either of it ſelfe to cauſe beliefe, or elſe to deſerve it at Gods hands:) this doubtleſſe his proud meaning, otherwiſe he had not affirmed in the following page, that God hath no reaſon to bee offended with thoſe, which uſing their beſt endeavours are miſtaken; and more hideouſly to this purpoſe in the following lines <note n="c" place="margin">I ſay plainly &amp; clearely, for he that ſpeaketh obſcurely and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guouſly, and now declares himſelfe plainly, ſurely hee hath no reaſon to be much offended if he bee miſtaken.</note>: which I wonder not ſo much at, when I conſider from whom they come, from a Sceptick in Divinity, and a changeling in Religion; a juſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on him, which ſo much relies on the ſtrength of reaſon, and the uſe of his own beſt endeavours; but this my wonder, (or griefe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) what great ones he hath (great (I mean) for their then eſteeme in the Chriſtian world) ready preſt as it were to bee his ſeconds: What elſe meane ſuch large approbations, making way for his Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianiſme? Lament may we with <hi>David</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.19.</note>, <hi>The beauty of Iſrael is ſlain upon thy high places, how are the mighty fallen? (Non homo voluntate ſuâ</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auſtine) adhuc in vitio liberi arbitrii claudicantis praevenit Deum, ut cognoſcat &amp; quarat eam gratiam,</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Lib. <hi>7.</hi> contra Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lag.</note>) mans will faultring, through the miſ-uſe of his former freedome doth not prevent God, <hi>by uſe of his beſt endeavours by doing what he can, his uſing ſuch a meaſure of induſtry in finding of truth, his humane prudence, and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary diſcretion,</hi> (as our Defender would make us beleeve in his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quoted paſſage) doth not, I ſay, prevent God in knowing or ſeeking his grace, which deſervedly he may challenge, <hi>(ſed praecedit miſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiſſimâ gratiâ ſuâ Deus hominis ignorantis, &amp; nondum ſe quaereutis
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:53814:19"/>voluntatem liberi arbitrii, ut eam ſe ſcire &amp; quarere faciat,</hi>) but God with his moſt free grace makes the will of man willingly to finde and know him, which naturally and of himſelfe is ignorant and careleſſe of him: And as 'tis the free mercy of God which begins this great bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe of converſion in man, ſo 'tis alſo his free grace which furthers and perfects it. In this reſpect may we ſay, what in another God himſelf ſayes <note n="f" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>When he begins he will alſo make an end,</hi> for 'tis <hi>he alone which of his good pleaſure worketh in us both to will and to do</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil,</hi> 2.13.</note> Know therefore in the laſt place, that graces though never ſo many and glorious, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not afford juſt matter of ſelf-boaſting; let me therefore in the laſt place ask thee, Why doſt thou boaſt thy ſelfe in thy ſpirituall graces?</p>
            <p>What if in many aſſaults thou haſt got the better of the field, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>more then Conquerour,</hi> yet remember <hi>'twas through Chriſt only, which loved you</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ram.</hi> 8.37</note>, and if the Lord had not been on thy ſide, mayſt thou now ſay, if the Lord had not been on thy ſide, when not men only, but when the World and the Devill, nay when thou didſt riſe up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy ſelfe, thou hadſt been ſwallowed up quick. Againe how knoweſt thou whether or no the Lord owes thee a forſaking; and 'tis more then probable he doth and will pay it too, if thou too much prideſt thy ſelfe, and turneſt his graces into wantonneſſe: When <hi>Ioh</hi> ſo ſecurely and ſo proudly too, <hi>My root is ſpread out by the waters and the dew layes all night upon my branch, my glory is freſh in mee, and my how is renewed in my hand</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 29.19</note> and ſo triumphantly to the end of the Chapter: ſee how ſadly the next chapter begins, <hi>Now they that are younger then me have me in deciſion, whoſe fathers I would have diſdai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to have ſet with the dogs of my flock:</hi> Thus <hi>David</hi> too, no ſooner had boaſted that in his proſperity, <hi>he ſhould never be moved, Lord by thy favour thou haſt made my mountaine to ſtand ſtrong,</hi> but preſontly it followes, <hi>thou didſt hide thy face from me, and I was troubled</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 30.6.7.</note>, Now if God once withdraw himſelfe, ſuffers thee to fall in a skirmiſh, let <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> teares and groanes and ſighes tell thee, how ſtrong throwes 'twill coſt ere thou recovereſt thy ſelfe or thy right ſtation. Once more, 'Twere better to have no grace at all (as the Father thinks) then that thou ſhouldſt make it matter of ſelf-boaſting, [<hi>Audeo dicere</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſuperhis continentibus expedit caders, ut in eo ipſo in quoſe extollunt hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milientur</hi>] I dare affirme it greater ſafety for the chaſt to fall, then to be proud of their chaſtity, that they might be humbled in that wherein they prided themſelves: and the reaſon is good he gives, <hi>[quid enim prodeſt continentia ſi dominetur ſuperbia?]</hi> what doth continency ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:53814:19"/>a man whom pride ſwels <note n="l" place="margin">Auſt. Serm. <hi>57.</hi> in Mat.</note>? He who thinks out of grace freely beſtowed to get glory to himſelfe, labours to the utmoſt to pull down what God was building, and to rebuild what God was pulling down, (i.) he is proud of his humility, humility being that which God ſeeks chiefly to erect, and pride that which hee ſeeks chiefly to pull down. A man in this caſe like <hi>Lots</hi> wife looks back on what the Lord was deſtroying, and 'tis the Lords meere mercy, that for an example he leaves not ſuch a one as he left her at the half-wayes end, even in the midſt of his journey to heaven; that it befals not him, as it did <hi>Eleazar</hi> who in fight firſt kild an Elephant, and afterward un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily by its fall was kild by the Elephant: ſo 'tis I ſay Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that whoſoever having conquered pride, and afterwards is proud of his conqueſt (of his humility) is not at laſt overcome by this pride.</p>
            <p>But me thinks the ſad conſequences of <hi>Peters</hi> boaſts ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently fright us from being guilty of the like; for as of him, ſo of others alſo is it generally obſerved both by Divines and Souldiers that the greateſt Braggadochio's are the firſt which revolt and deny; nay rather then they'l hazard life or goods, the firſt that will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare too: Wot you not that <hi>Peter</hi> which ere whilſt made that great vaunt, <hi>Though all men ſhould bee offended becauſe of thee, yee will I never bee offended</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Malth.</hi> 26.33.</note>, immediately afterwards, <hi>ourſt and ſwore he knew him not</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 76.</note>? and pray obſerve that 'tis plaine from the content that this his revolting was not ſo much an argument of his weak faith, as a puniſhment of his preſumption: There are a ſort of Thraſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall Profeſſours alwayes boaſting how farre they dare goe in a good cauſe, which either ruffile it in a bad, or will not venture a being wer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhod in a good, men much like theſe <hi>Galli Inſubros</hi> (<hi>Florus</hi> ſpeaks of <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lih.</hi> 2.</note>) which had <hi>[corpora plus quàm humana]</hi> bore a good bulk and ſhow, <hi>[quorum primus impetus iis major quâm virorum crat, ſequens verò minor quàm foeminarum]</hi> who at the firſt onſet were valiant almoſt beyond men, but in the heat of the battell co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards below women: So theſe forward men (as they ſeeme) at the firſt like thornes make a great blaze and noiſe, yet ſuddenly goe out: notwithſtanding ſome ſmall penalty or diſgrace they ſwell'd and bufled, yet now, now, when there is happily a neceſſity of endange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, if not leaving off all that we may follow Chriſt, now there is laying down of lives for his ſake: now (as that Hiſterian ſpeaks of theſe <hi>Galli</hi>) they have <hi>[quaddam ſimile oum nevibus,]</hi> like ſoow they quickly diſſolve and are loſt, either they goe beyond Sea, thereby to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:53814:20"/>quit themſelves of trouble and expence, or elſe (like <hi>Metius Fuffetius</hi> in <hi>Florus</hi>) they ſtand aloft and indifferent, reſolving at laſt to ſide with the uppermoſt, or elſe <hi>[in malum otium reſoluti]</hi> (as <hi>Tacitus</hi> of <hi>Tibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Annal. l. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note>) prizing their own eaſe and quiet before the welfare of the State, they doe with <hi>Tiberius</hi> betake themſelves <hi>[in inſulam Capreas]</hi> into ſome nook or by-corner of the Countrey, caring not, ſo they may ſleep in a whole skinne, what become of Liberty, or Religion: and of theſe wee may ſafely ſay, what <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Darius</hi> his ſouldiers, [<hi>Temeritas eſt quam adhuc pro virtute habuiſtis, quae ubi pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum impetum effudit, velut quaedam animalia amiſſo aculco, torpet</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Qu. Curt. b. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note>], this fierce entrance, which ſome vaine-glorious and haſty men have made, was not (as fondly it was imagined) vertue and Religion, but pride and headineſſe; when their firſt heate and pranſing was paſt they ſuddenly flagged, like bees having loſt their ſtings become droanes: In vaine therefore did ſuch beat the eares of men wiſe and religious with that bold boaſt of <hi>Jehu's, [Come ſee my zeal for the Lord of hoaſts]</hi> for who with halfe an eye ſees not that therefore they went from us, becauſe they were never of us? And ſo farre of the ſecond branch of the firſt queſtion, its ground and reaſon; a word only of application, and I ſhall forward to the laſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Applic. </seg>
               </label> From what hath been laid againſt priding our ſelves in any thing we call our own, we may gather juſt matter of humiliation: be then perſwaded not onely from the conſideration of the frailty of the good things of the body, and the vanity, emptineſſe, and uncertainty of the good things (we call Fortunes,—<hi>nete quaeſiveris extra</hi>) that thou makeſt not concluſions of thy ſelfe according to thy flouriſhing in the world (thus farre the Heathen could goe) but alſo from the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of that miſerable, dead and ignorant condition thou art in by nature, renounce thy ſelfe, (all carnall props and ſtaies) and ſeek the Lords favour with an humble ſoule, that if thou wilt glory thou maiſt glory in the Lord, that thou maiſt have wherewithall truly to hug and glad thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Nothing will more humble us then the meditation of our own wretchedneſſe by nature, 'twill allay our pride in us, 'tis like the Peacocks looking on his feet, it pulls down our plumes, to conſider on what we are bottomed; our foundation is not onely in the earth, but in rotten putrified earth, we are not onely fraile but corrupted fleſh. Tell me, could the proud and ſtour heart of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> be ſtill ſoaring and ſwell, when from a King he was turned into a beaſt? and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:53814:20"/>can wee be then proud and vaine-glorious boaſters of our own natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall abilities, when we ſhall call to minde this miſerable conſequence of <hi>Adams</hi> fall, that from being Kings of the whole earth, we are turn'd into beaſts, yes worſethen beaſts, witneſſe ſuch hideous corruptions continually breaking forth which the worſt of beaſts were never guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of? Shall <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> from the conſideration of his lameneſſe; and the fall of his parents be ſo humbled, that <hi>he bowed himſelfe unto David and ſaid, What is thy ſervant, that thou ſhouldſt look upon ſuch a dead dog as I am</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sam.</hi> 9.8.</note>? And can we, when we ſhall conſider that we are all of us more lame ſpiritually, then ever <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> was corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, and infinitely more endammaged by the fall of our Parents, then he by his, continue ſtill confident of our naturall ſtrength? For, firſt, our lameneſſe is much more then his; he maimed in one part only, we bruiſed all over; hee from the cradle onely, we from the womb; he procured his maimedneſſe from his Nurce, we from our firſt Parents: For as <hi>Auſtine</hi> of <hi>Adam</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Tom. T.P. <hi>276.</hi> A.</note>, <hi>[Omnes ille unus fuere]</hi> all of us were he, and he was all of us. Againe, infinitely more are wee endammaged by their fall; he by the fall of his Parents loſt onely an Inheritance to a little patch of earth, to a temporary kingdome, to an uneaſie uncertaine crown: but we our right to the whole world, to an heavenly Kingdome, and an eternall weight of glory. Once more, if <hi>Leah</hi> by reaſon of her blear'd eyes, and the little favour ſhe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by found in the ſight of <hi>Iacob,</hi> was afflicted, (ſurely ſaith ſhe, <hi>the Lord hath look't upon my affliction</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 29.32.</note>,) how will it afflict our ſoules then, when we ſhall truly know that we are not only as tender eyed as <hi>Leah,</hi> but as blind as <hi>Bartimens?</hi> For being alienated from the life of God (as by nature we are) <hi>We have our underſtandings darkned through the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance that is in us by reaſon of the blindneſſe of our hearts</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.18.</note>: and <hi>if the light that is in us bee dark, how great is that darkneſſe</hi> 
               <note n="w" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 6.23.</note>? Nay, herein lies the great cauſe of our miſery and humiliation, that we are not onely naturally blind, but giddy and unruly, notwithſtanding this our blindneſſe: by the reaſon of the diſobedience of <hi>Adam,</hi> that curſe is fallen on us, which was threatned to the diſobedient Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.28.</note>, wee are ſmitten not onely with blindneſſe, but with madneſſe too: and as a man ſober and blind underſtands his miſery, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by keeping within or ſitting ſtill, is alwayes out of dangers and whereas one mad and blind expoſes himſelfe to variety of dangers and miſeries: Even this our caſe, we are abſolutely by nature blind, nay blindneſſe it ſelfe; (<hi>Yee were ſometimes darkneſſe</hi> (ſaith S.<hi>Paul</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 58.</note>) in the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:53814:21"/>ſtate of nature before you were called by the Word and Spirit, yee were not onely blind, but in the abſtract blindneſſe it ſelfe) and yet ſo mad are we that we ſtrive <hi>by our naturall endeavours, by our ſtrength of reaſon, and humane prudence and ordinary diſcretion,</hi> (I ſhall never make that paſſage of our Defenders ſufficiently odious) to find out the truth, in ſo much that the Lord (we conclude) is unreaſonable, if ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving truths are not underſtood by us, of if we are puniſhed for not ſavingly underſtanding of them <note n="z" place="margin">This concluſion took from the Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians <hi>vid. Auſt. Tom.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 458. <hi>D.</hi>
               </note> And this miſery we bring on our ſelves, even the miſery following madneſſe joyned with blindneſſe, <hi>a groping at noone-day</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.28.29.</note>, even now when the light of the Goſpel is gloriouſly and plentifully afforded us, when the Sunne is at its full ſhine and heigh: even now there is groping up and down for the truth, from Proteſtantiſme to Popery they goe, and from Popery to Proteſtantiſme, and thence are poſting back againe, and meetly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are mad as well as blind, whereas were they truly ſenſible of their naturall blindneſſe and darkneſſe, in ſtead of venturing abroad thus blind, they would with <hi>Bartimens, ſit ſtill, be quiet,</hi> and betake themſelves wholly to Chriſt, crying out him <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.47.51.</note>, <hi>Ieſus thou Sonne of of David, have mercy on me; This Lord I will, that I might receive my fight:</hi> Then ſhall it be with them, as 'twas with him, <hi>their faith ſhall make them whole, they ſhall receive their ſight</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 52.</note>, then only may they venture abroad, and be able to follow Ieſus on the way.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, can we imagine that the curſe of <hi>Eliſha</hi> on <hi>Gehezi</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 5 <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note>, not bow and ſink him, <hi>The leproſie therefore of Naaman ſhall cleave un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee and thy ſeed for ever, and he went out from his preſence a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per as white as ſnow?</hi> How can it then but humble us, to conſider that as a juſt puniſhment of our firſt ſinne, God hath ſaid the leproſie of <hi>Adam</hi> ſhall cleave unto us and our ſeed for ever, and we are ever ſince borne leprous all over, no part of us free from the crown of the head to the ſole of the foot <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſ.</hi> 1.6.</note>? <hi>In primopeccato</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tilenus) perſons corrupit naturam, in originali natura corrumpit perſonam</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Syntag. li.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 56. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.</note>, in the firſt ſinne man corrupted nature, but ſince in originall ſinne, out heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary leproſie, nature corrupts the man; children even of the beſt and holieſt Chriſtians are borne covered with this leproſie, (<hi>quomodo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putium manet in tis quos genuerint circumciſi, &amp; palea in fructu qui de purgato tritico naſcitur</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Auſt. Tom.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 276. <hi>c.</hi>
               </note> juſt as children begot by cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed Parents bring notwithſtanding their fore-skinne with them, or as the fruit of the beſt winnowed wheat ſpring up wrapt in chaffe: In a word, to conſider what lameneſſe and blindneſſe, what
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:53814:21"/>bruiſes and leproſie, what cruſhings and depravedneſſe, as a juſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of our firſt fall is brought on us, ſhould mightily humble us, becauſe Gods judgments are not laid on us ſo much to puniſh as to humble us for ſinne, to bring us to the knowledge of that death and ſhame which is in ſinne by afflicting us for it, [<hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, I will puniſh the world for their evill, and the wicked for their iniquity, and I will cauſe the arrogancy of the pround to ceaſe, and will lay low the haughtineſſe of the terrible</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſ</hi> 13.11.</note>,] as if the Lord ſhould ſay, to this end men ſhall ſuffer, not onely that they might be puniſhed, but that they might bee humbled, <hi>that their arrogancy might ceaſe,</hi> and that their haughtineſſe might be laid low. God forbid, that the Church of <hi>Laodicea's</hi> caſe ſhould be ours, either that we ſhould be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of our miſerable condition by nature, ſhould not know that we are wretched and miſerable, poor, &amp; blind, &amp; naked, and not knowing thus much, ſhould think our ſelves ſufficienly rich and wanting no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; and upon theſe falſe thoughts ſwell and extoll our ſelves, build caſtles in the ayre, promiſe our ſelves ſafety, and ſalvation to be got by our own naturall ſtrength and abilities, when truth is, theſe will prove caſtles in the ayre indeed, weak and nothing: And ſo much of the ſecond branch of the firſt Queſtion, the third fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Branch </seg>3</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>To what end doſt thou boaſt thy ſelfe?</hi> it being already manifeſted that there is no juſt reaſon why thou poor fraile nothing man ſhouldſt boaſt thy ſelfe, and ſecondly, that thou haſt nothing whereof thou maiſt juſtly boaſt. We ſhall have the leſſe labour to prove, thou canſt have no right end in thy boaſting; let mee therefore in a few words ask thee, to what end doſt thou boaſt thy ſelfe? But alas, I may not expect an anſwer to my queſtion, for I am confident that the verieſt Captaine, the higheſt creſted of this proud Regiment would bluſh to acknowledge the empty fond end their vaunting aimes at, and I wiſh that they would bluſh alſo to heare it, that the reſt may diſcover and laugh at them; for I purpoſe to ſpeak truth for them, and try whether their guilty faces will confeſſe what their tongues dare not: (Hearken) the whole onely maine end of theſe ſelfe-boaſting men is mearely and nothing elſe but the <hi>Euge,</hi> and the <hi>Bellè,</hi> the popular, <hi>Oh brave, oh admirable, oh honeſt!</hi> The clap and cry, the throat and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe of the giddy multitude of wondring ignorants, <hi>(riſum tenea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis amici?)</hi> 'Tis a juſt complaint of the French mans <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mountaig. Eſſay l,</hi> 2.6.16.</note> that wee uſually empanell and ſelect a jury of men out of a whole County
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:53814:22"/>to determine of an houſe or an acre of Land, but the judgment, and determination of our ſelves, we referre to the idle breath of common people, <hi>[An quicquam ſtultius, quèm quos ſingulos contemnes, eos aliquid putares eſſe univerſos?]</hi> can their be a greater folly then to eſteeme of their full cry, whoſe particular mouthes thou wouldſt ſcorne?</p>
            <q>Gloria quantalibet quid erit, ſi gloria tantum?</q>
            <p>What is glory if thou haſt nothing elſe to make it good? nay if thou haſt a ſubſtance whereof that is the ſhadow, yet ſtill may it be askt, <hi>Gloria quantalibet quid erit?</hi> What is the prayſe and eſteem which men afford thy vertues, which is ſo blind and unequall, that well may it be termed a ſhadow: For as the ſhadow is never juſtly proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the dimenſions of thy body; ſo nor this to thy deſert: the worlds eſteeme like the ſhadow in the morning and beginning of thy Sun when thou firſt appeareſt, and art cryed up, is farrelarger then thy deſert, but in the midſt and prime of the day, when thou art beſt and moſt deſerving, then uſually this thy ſhadow comes farre ſhort of thee, thou ſhalt not have halfe the glory thou meriteſt: and as a ſhadow ſometimes goes before the body, and ſometimes followes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſo many ſteale glory from the ignorant world ere their deſert cals for't, and ſome again whoſe lives have been excellently good &amp; exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary have dyed in diſgrace, yet their <hi>works and glory have followed them</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.13.</note>, and their names ſmell ſweet upon earth. Let then children, and Poets, Players, and Painters, hunt after the clap and cry of the times; let light tottering Chriſtians follow the faſhion even in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion too; let Popelings hug and vaunt themſelves in their outſide boaſting and meerely ceremonious devotions: but let us, us whoſe hope and aime 'tis to be thoſe little ones, (our Saviour ſpeaks of <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Malli.</hi> 18.6.</note>) little in our own conceits, and little in the worlds; let, I ſay, us neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the vaine empty glory the world affords, earneſtly ſeek after the maſſie and weighty glory, humility ſhall enjoy in heaven, a glory of that bulk and ſubſtance, that where <hi>David</hi> ſayes, [<hi>thou O Lord art my glory</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3.3.</note>] the originall ſignifies his weightineſſe and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity; which place I beleeve, S. <hi>Paul</hi> had reſpect unto, when hee call'd it an exceeding eternall weight of glory <note n="n" place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17.</note> And here I thought to make the application of this third branch, the continuance of this exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hoping to have ſome of theſe tinkling Cymbals, theſe outſide men hereby to be perſwaded off from their affectation of vaine-glory, but I have conſidered that there is more good to be done upon theſe fawning Curs by a knock then by a gentle put-off; I ſhall therefore change my intended exhortation into a reproofe.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:53814:22"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Applic. </seg>
               </label> There are a ſort amongſt us, that ſaile only with a popular wind, they continue not good and faſt out of the ſound of a <hi>Bellè</hi> or an <hi>Euge,</hi> which they ſo greedily thirſt after, that they had rather have an O brave, bellowing in their eares by the ignorant rout, then a Well done good and faithfull ſervant, ſounded to their conſciences by their Saviour: and this our miſery, that not ſome few of the lower forme only, but thoſe of the higheſt, ſome otherwiſe fit for the ſterne, great ones ('tis to bee feared) live by this ayre. To ſee a little Spaniell or Tumbler with his ſneaking and fawning to beg a commending clap on the ſide, or ſpetting in the mouth is ſomewhat tolerable; but to ſee a great old Maſtiffe riggle for it, after the ſame ridiculous geſture is extreamly odious. In like manner to ſee a Player or Fencer to expect or take courage from the clap or ſhout of giddy Spectatours, 'tis as pardonable as uſuall; but to ſee this old Stateſ-man, or t'other great Souldier, which ought to bee ſerious and in earneſt, Chamelion-like to live by the common aire, to wax cold or hot in their weighty employments according to the cry of vulgar Ignorants, 'twould make a man loſe both patience and modeſty; and tell this great Lord or t'other great man, that the Compaſſe he ſteares by, is unworthy either his blood place, honour, or calling, and that this common aire he now lives by, is of all aires moſt uncertaine and altering, and may through ſudden diſlike become ſufficiently thick and noiſome to ſtifle or poyſon him, and that happily not undeſerving. For to ſpeak truth, the vaine glorious ones of our times, are the loweſt and unworthyeſt that ever I read or heard of. Hiſtory wil tell you that <hi>Scevola</hi> burnt his own hand off; <hi>Zeleucus</hi> ſuffered one of his own, and another of his Sons eyes to bee boared out; <hi>Decius</hi> flung himſelfe into the midſt of a bloody and raging Army, intending thereby to become a ſacrifice for his Countrey; and <hi>Brutus</hi> too whipt and beheaded his two Sons in one day, and all theſe moved by the ſame ground and principle, even as the Hiſtorian reports of that act of <hi>Brutus</hi> his (<hi>favore civium</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Flor. lib. 2.</note>) to gaine favour from the people: and what ſpirit and reſolution this ſpark of vaine-glory put into ſome Chriſtians in the Primitive times, Doctor <hi>Donne</hi> tells you <note n="p" place="margin">Pſeudo-Mart.</note>, whereas he excellently diſcovers, and right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly blames their inordinate affectation of Martyrdome. But alas, the vaine-glory-hunters of our times, though that only byaſſes them, yet can it not thus ſtrongly byaſſe them; though <hi>(favor civium)</hi> be the thing they onely aime at, and the wheele theſe puppets onely move by, yet baſe as they are, baſe below Chriſtians in the infancy
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:53814:23"/>of the Church, nay baſe below Heathens, yet will they not venture on any danger or hazzard any loſſe to gaine or continue it Let theſe take home that of <hi>Tertullians, [haec ethnicorum exempla non ſine cauſâ Dominus in ſeculum admiſit, ſed ad nos &amp; nunc exhortandos, &amp; in illo die confundendos, ſi reformidaverimus pati pro veritate in ſalutem, quae alii affectaverunt in perditionem</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Lib. ad Martyr.</note>], theſe forenamed examples of the Heathens God did not in vaine, but for us admit of, both for our preſent encouragement, and for our ſhame and confuſion, if we ſhall through ſca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſhrink from under-going theſe miſeries for the truth unto eternall ſalvation, which they for vaine-glory only affected unto their condemnation. The neceſſary brunts, hazzards and troubles, theſe our preſent diſtractions put good men upon, abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly diſcover theſe empty <hi>quelque choſes.</hi> Now, even now, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſayes unto them, If you'l follow me, ſhew your ſelves my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, goe and venture all that you have for me, and you ſhall have treaſures in heaven: like the young man in the Goſpel upon the like injunction and tryall, they are not only ſorrowfull, beginne to flag and to be diſcontented, to repent that they have gone ſo farre, ſtickled ſo much for Chriſt, but with the young man too, they begin to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, (ſhame to them) and forſake him, and upon the ſame ground too, as the young man there did <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 2.19.21.22.</note>, <hi>becauſe they have great poſſeſſions:</hi> when their ſtore of Land, or great Houſes come in queſtion, then farewell reputation and popularity, theſe ſhall no longer keep them in trouble or danger, they will then tell you, as the Spaniard ſayes truly of ſuch <note n="ſ" place="margin">Fanſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ſerm. <hi>37.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>[That obligation of Religion is not ſo preciſe a thing that we ſhould for the ſame adventure either our goods, perſons, or peace of the State: That which a Stateſ-man is most intereſted in, is the profit and benefit of the people, and by no meanes ought he to draw too much envie upon them for cauſe of religion:]</hi> So true is that of S. <hi>Pauls, [Not many wiſe men after the fleſh, not many noble are called</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.26.</note>]: And that of our Saviours, [<hi>Arich man ſhall hardly enter into the Kingdom of Heaven</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 19.23.</note>]. And ſo much be ſpoken of the firſt part of the queſtion in generall, and of its three particular branches; in the laſt place fall wee upon its ſecond part, I ſay in the laſt place, becauſe my meditations on the firſt queſtion have enlarged themſelves ſo much farther then at firſt was intended, that I ſhall have no time to handle the laſt queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, unleſſe I touch on it in the application of the ſecond.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Why doſt thou boaſt thy ſelfe in miſchiefe?</hi> To juſtifie this carneſt expoſtulation of my Pſalmiſt, I ſhall ſhew you out of the ſacred
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:53814:23"/>Hiſtory what a ſearfull and hideous miſchiefe this boaſter, whether <hi>Saul</hi> the Tyrant, or <hi>Doeg</hi> the bloody miſleading informer, was guilty of, and leave it to your after meditations to make the concluſion, whether or no they have juſt cauſe to boaſt of it, or the Pſalmiſt to be amazed and loſt at their boaſting. <hi>David</hi> was ſo much in the peoples eyes, [<hi>Saul hath ſlaine his thouſand and David his tenne thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands</hi> 
               <note n="w" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.7.</note>,] that he therefore became leſſe in <hi>Saul's, [and Saul eyed Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid from that day forward</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">verſ. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note>,] This emulation, or rather envie bred wrath, the wrath a murderous intention, [<hi>and Saul caſt a javelin, for he ſaid, I will ſmite David even to the wall with it</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">verſ. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note>,] So much danger did <hi>David</hi> finde, there was in deſerving and being thought well of by the people; the Kings violence thus miſſing its aime, he turnes his rage into wiles, of an <hi>Ajax</hi> becomes an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes,</hi> drops preferment to enſnare him <note n="z" place="margin">verſ. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note>; afterwards upon <hi>Ionathans</hi> plaine dealing pacifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is made and the King binds it with a ſolemn Oath, [<hi>As the Lord liveth he ſhall not be ſlaine</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.6</note>,] and immediately breaks that Oath and Pacification, and through the evill Spirit that was upon him, <hi>ſought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to ſmite him to the wall with his Javelin</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">verſ. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note>; anon after <hi>David</hi> being certified by <hi>Ionathan</hi> of his Fathers murderous intentions <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Sam. <hi>20.</hi> à ver. <hi>37.</hi> ad <hi>41.</hi>
               </note>, was forc't to flie for his life, and in his flight betook himſelfe to <hi>Ahimelech</hi> the Prieſt for reliefe and ſuccour, and ſo well told he his tale, that he got of him the Shew-bread, and <hi>Goliah's</hi> Sword <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Sam. <hi>21</hi> àver. <hi>6.</hi> ad <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> But ſee the ground and Author of this great miſchiefe, <hi>Doeg</hi> was then in the Temple, and heard all, (as 'tis the peculiar lot of Gods people to fall into the hands of <hi>Doegs,</hi> treacherous and deceitfull people) this ſneaking Paraſite carries and aggravates the buſineſſe to <hi>Saul, [I ſaw the Sonne of</hi> Ieſſe <hi>comming to Nob to Ahimelech the Prieſt, and he enquired of the Lord for him</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.9.10.</note>], and what of that? 'twas after treaſon and conſpiracy the King enquired, [<hi>ſed ea ratio eſt adulatorum, ut ſi principem calentem videant, velint eum incenderc, &amp; ex ſtulto prorſus inſanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> facere</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pet. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr in loc.</note>,] but ſuch is the condition of flatterers that they'l blow a heated Tyrant into a flame, and turne his folly into madneſſe; Upon this falſe information <hi>Ahimelech</hi> and the reſt of the Prieſts with all of their Families were ſent for <note n="g" place="margin">ver. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note>; they come, <hi>Saul</hi> becomes both the accuſer and the Judge, and preſently falls upon the tryall, [<hi>Heare now thou Sonne of Ahituh, and he anſwered, Here am I: and Saul ſaid unto him, Why have yee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired against me</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 12.13.</note>?] But wherein laid the conſpiracy? in relieving a man faithfull to his God and Prince? [<hi>And who is ſo faith full amongſt all thy Servants as David, which is the Kings Son in Law? [Conjuratio
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:53814:24"/>eſt conſenſus aliquorum contra rempub:</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Pet. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </note>]. The conſpire, which miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievouſly plot againſt the Common-Wealth: [<hi>he goeth at thy bidding and is honourable in thy houſe];</hi> did he then begin to enquire of God for him <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 14.15.</note>? <hi>i.e.</hi> is this the firſt time I enquired for him? or being thy Son-in-law, and thy faithfull Servant, I did not ſo much enquire of God for him, as for thee. At laſt knowing he was to deale with a Tyrant, whom reaſon, law or right would nothing move, hee gives over pleading and falls to begging, <hi>[Let not the King impute any thing to thy Servant, for thy Servant knew nothing of this more or leſſe</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">ver. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note>]: What if you had <hi>Ahimelech?</hi> would you not therefore have relieved him, becauſe the King unjuſtly perſecured him? would that have beene faire dealing (think you?) If others had been of this minde, he had never overcome the Tyrants cruelty. But now I ſee that our Prieſts (as they deſire to be cald) are not the firſt that would rather renounce a juſt cauſe, then diſpleaſe an unjuſt man: Our cruell High-Prieſt, violent and peremptory as he was, did with his power ſo brow-beat and dare all the reſt (as one of themſelves lately and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely confeſt) that they had but one voice amongſt them all, the reſt being but his ecchoe's, his dictates out-noiſ'd thoſe of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: for woe had been to them who had done otherwiſe, who had relieved any though never ſo innocent and religious, whom his Grace had ſlung his Iavelin at, ſent his Citation for, or once cal'd Puritane —<hi>Rubet auditor, cui frigida mens est.]</hi> But to goe forwards, would this Prieſt his cloſing with <hi>Saul</hi> ſerve his turne? no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, <hi>[For the King ſaid, Thou ſhalt ſurely die Ahimelech, thou and all thy Fathers houſe</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">ver. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note>:] The ſentence is paſt, between which and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution ſome reſpite ought to be, but no ſuch matter now, he immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately ſayes unto the foot-men that were about him Turne and ſlay the Prieſts of the Lord <note n="n" place="margin">ver. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note>, fearing happily leſt cooling and comming to himſelfe he might on better conſideration not have been guilty of ſo much innocent blood: But wherefore ſhould they be ſlaine? <hi>Becauſe they knew when David fled and told it not unto me:</hi> but where is the witneſſe? <hi>Doeg</hi> you'l ſay did affirme it: but is not this againſt the known Law <note n="o" place="margin">Deut. <hi>17.6</hi>
               </note>, <hi>[At the mouth of two or three witneſſes ſhall hee that is worthy of death, die, but at the mouth of one witneſſe he ſhall not die?]</hi> But ſee, the honeſt Guard farre honeſter then their maſter, would not put forth their hand to fall upon the Prieſts of the Lord <note n="p" place="margin">verſ. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note>, they well know he was but Gods Miniſter for their good, <hi>&amp; mandatorius ſiquid vult facere contra mandatum, id jubet eſſe irritum</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">et. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </note>, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:53814:24"/>a Commiſſioner injoynes beyond his Commiſſion is voide, and ought not to be obeyed. But if one won't another will, the Devill will alwayes ſupply Tyrants with ſuitable inſtruments; <hi>Doeg</hi> ſeemes to be glad of the office, and reſolute to doe whatſoever the King ſhould command him, never interpoſing that honeſt condition of the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites to <hi>Ioſhua, [onely the Lord be with thee</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">Ioſh. <hi>1.17.</hi>
               </note>] and forthwith he fals to work, fell on the Prieſts of the Lord, <hi>and ſlew on that day foureſcore and five perſons, that wore a linnen Ephod</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.18.</note>: he ſlew the Prieſts, the Prieſts of the Lord, he ſlew men unarm'd, men conſecrated to God, he ſlew old men and women, he ſlew children and ſucklings, to whom Scythians and Parthians have ſhown mercy in the time of the cruelleſt warre; and to make up the ſumme, he ſlew ſo many innocents, he ſlew them, he their informer was their executioner; firſt bely'd them with his tongue, and then butchered them with his hand: chuſe which you will now, either <hi>Saul</hi> or his inſtrument, and you cannot but confeſſe there is cauſe more then enough of my Pſalmiſts queſtion and excla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, [Why doſt thou <hi>Saul,</hi> thou envious, malitious, unjuſt, bloody Tyrant, or why doſt thou <hi>Doeg,</hi> thou ſneaking baſe informing Paraſite, thou cruell murdering butcher, why doſt thou boaſt thy ſelfe in this ſo unheard of a miſchief?] But happily, &amp; on good grounds, <hi>Davids</hi> won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may be that any whatſoever ſhould boaſt in any whatſoever miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, &amp; therfore I ſhal endeavor to make good the queſtion in general.</p>
            <p>And now (me thinks) I am brought into a wilderneſſe, the ſubject I am fallen on, is ſo large and fearefull; ſhould I let fly my Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, with that bitterneſſe and liberty wherewith ſuch mad and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious boaſters ought to be took up, I ſhould loſe both you and my ſelfe. But the ſutableneſſe of my firſt queſtions buſineſſe, both to our times and our preſent occaſion, tempted me to ſo much over-large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that I could not but in equity promiſe brevity in the following queſtons: that therefore I may bee as good as my word, I ſhall not keep you long in this wilderneſſe. Mad and prodigious boaſters have I cald them, and truly both theſe they are. Firſt, they are mad, for who but a mad man would boaſt that he had given himſelf his deaths wound? [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>ſinne is the death of the ſoule</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.12.13.</note> Who but a mad man would boaſt of that heavie burden, he is forc't night and day to ſink under? [<hi>a heavie burden are my iniquities</hi> (faith <hi>David</hi>) <hi>they are too heavie for me</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. <hi>38.4.</hi>
               </note>]. This heavie burthen the Prophet cals a <hi>Talent of Lead</hi> 
               <note n="w" place="margin">Zach. <hi>5.7.</hi>
               </note>; yes, heavier and more intolerable then Hell or the Devill himſelfe, for 'twas ſinne made Hell, and 'twas ſin
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:53814:25"/>ſunk the Devill into it; without it he cannot adde a dram weight to depreſſe or keep us from making towards heaven; nay, though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly, hee furthers us in the way; but 'tis ſinne alone, and only which keeps us down. Again, who but a mad man would boaſt in what arrerages he runnes with his Creditours, vauntingly publiſh, how all hee hath is morgaged, and that Vſury eates him up apace? 'tis truth indeed ſome may, and many do, (baſe and unworthy as they are) pretend poverty, ſay, that they are ready to ſtarve, that thereby they might ſtarve Chriſts cauſe. But I cannot deeme that man truly himſelfe, which really boaſts how bravely he is undone. Now to obey Gods law is a debt due from us to him, [<hi>Curſed is hee that continueth not in all the words of the Law to doe them</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.26.</note> 
               <hi>and all the people ſhall Amen:</hi>] that obedience is our debt we cannot deny, our conſciences ſeale to this bond, the counterpane of it is wrote even in every na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall mans heart <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.15</note>; every ſinne then being a tranſgreſſion of the Law is an arrerage, and upon this arrerage the ſoule is morgaged, and without repentance loſt and forfeited, the ſinner is utterly undone, he ſhall be delivered up unto the tormentor untill he hath paid all his debt <note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.34.</note> Once more, who but a mad man will boaſt that he is a loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome creature? <hi>a wicked man is a loathſome man</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 13.5.</note>) loathſome in Gods eyes, [<hi>my ſoule loaths him,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.8.</note>] loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome in the eyes of good-men; and not only loathſome, but infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous too: the Prophet therfore <hi>reſolved not to be in a wicked mans com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.5.</note>: Laſtly, it makes him loathſome and contemptible in the eyes of his neareſt friends, yea of thoſe friends which ought according to the Laws of God &amp; nature not only to love, but to reverence him. Thus the Prophet of <hi>Icruſalem,</hi> by reaſon of ſinne, [<hi>Icruſalem hath grievouſly ſinned</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.18</note> 
               <hi>therefore they that honoured her diſpiſed her;</hi>] and though for want of faith, and by reaſon of the weakneſſe of ſpirituall judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wee cannot diſcover the filth and uglineſſe of ſinne, yet doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe at Chriſts ſecond comming, when hee ſhall be revealed from Heaven, this alſo ſhall bee revealed, even what an ugly noiſome creature an impenitent ſinner is; <hi>then</hi> (ſaith the Prophet ſpeaking of Doomes-day and ſinners) <hi>they ſhall be an abhorring to all fleſh</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Iſ. <hi>66.</hi> ult.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, as theſe boaſters in miſchiefe are mad, ſo are they alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digiouſly wicked; for who but a man prodigiouſly wicked would boaſt that God is fallen out with him? ſuch a boaſter is he which boaſteth in ſinne, for 'tis <hi>ſinne that ſeparates between us and our God</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.2.</note>: ſecondly, every ſinne is a contempt againſt God <hi>(quo ejus pracepta contemnimus)
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:53814:25"/>temnimus</hi>] ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Serm. <hi>31.</hi> de mod. bene viven. di.</note>: how prodigiouſly then doth he contemn God, which boaſts that he hath contemned him? Thirdly, ſinne is that which excludes us heaven, and flings us into hell, that which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prives us of all that we call good, and brings on us all that is miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; 'tis the greateſt of curſes, and the worſt of judgements. Hence Saint <hi>Paul</hi> labouring to expreſſe how much Chriſt had ſuffered for us; ſayes [<hi>he was made ſinne for us</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21.</note>:] How prodigiouſly wicked then is he which boaſts of the greateſt miſery that man is capable of? Laſtly, ſin being that alone which crucified the Lord of life, which tore our Saviours head with thorns, pierc'd his ſide, &amp; nail'd his feet, which made him ſweat blood &amp; water, which put the gall and vinegar to his mouth, and wrung from him that bitter complaint, <hi>[My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me]</hi> Tell me then, ſadly tell me, is not he prodigiouſly wicked which boaſts in that which after ſo cruell and ſhamefull a manner crucified our Saviour?</p>
            <p>Nor is this boaſter in miſchiefe mad onely and prodigiouſly wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, but which muſt neceſſarily follow, and be ſuppoſed, is in a deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and forlorne caſe: and for theſe two reaſons. Firſt, becauſe ſuch a one ſinnes with the fulleſt ſwing and willingneſſe, without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctancy and ſcruple, nothing hath hee of the Spirit in him, which might cauſe oppoſition, or pawces, (<hi>The words of his mouth are int<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and deceit,</hi> as my Pſalmiſt of him, <hi>he hath left off to be wiſe and to doe good, hee deviſeth miſchiefe upon his bed, hee ſetteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. i. e.</hi> gladly goes on; <hi>in a way that is not good,</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 36.3.</note> 
               <hi>who being paſt feeling, hath given himſelfe over to worke all uncleanneſſe and greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.19.</note> Secondly, becauſe theſe of all men are fartheſt from Chriſt and heaven, being fartheſt from repentance, whoſe ſinnes are ſo farre from being a load and heavy burden unto them, that they glory in their ſhame. 'Tis with theſe boaſters as with men dived to the bottom of the water, as long as they lye in the water, they are nothing ſenſible of its weight, but once recovering out would be overwhelmed with a ſmall quantity of it: So theſe boaſters being ſunke to the bottome, almoſt as low as hell, and lying there under never ſo many and hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deous ſinnes, are never ſenfible of their load and burden, whereas to a man by Gods grace recovering out of them, one and the leaſt ſin will be a talent of Lead. And ſo much of this ſecond Queſtion; a ſhort ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, and I have done.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Applic. </seg>
               </label> And here let's pawſe a while, &amp; with our beſt and ſerious thoughts admire and lament the miſerable condition of our land, wherein ſo many of theſe madmen, of theſe prodigies, of theſe deſperately forlorn
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:53814:26"/>wretches ſwarme and ſpread amongſt us. Go abroad and liſten, and you ſhall hear the Drunkard boaſt how many ſwine he made the laſt night: you ſhall hear the Ruffler boaſt what a new handſome full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouthed oath he hath got: the Goat, how many women he hath abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: and the Fox, how many he hath over-reached and couſened:
<q>
                  <l>—Fiunt,</l>
                  <l>Fiunt iſta palam cupiunt &amp; in asta referri.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But alas! theſe, though miſcreants, are but novices and bunglers in reſpect of ſome cloſer workers, and deeper inſtruments of the devill, who firſt guild over ſin with the name of vertue, and boaſt of it under that name. Take ſome inſtances. Such are thoſe, which leſt they ſhould loſe friends or credit, dare not openly profeſſe how good they are at lies, yet will they affirme, that hand ſome lying is but policy, and boaſt how many they have over-reacht with thi their policy; Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury by no meanes will they juſtify, yet will they tell you that it is the part of a wiſe Stateſ-man, in caſe that the keeping of an oath hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders a project, to invent ſome cleanly ſhift, whereby it may be eluded, and boaſt how excellent they are at theſe ſhifts. Luke-warmneſſe, a <hi>Laodicean</hi> temper, may not be countenanced, yet this will they call moderation, &amp; boaſt themſelves in this their moderatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Obſtinacy in a wrong way, twere ſhame to patronize, yet this will they call a brave ſpirit, and boaſt of their own ſtout hearts: they will praiſe a <hi>Ioſiah</hi> for going on peremptorily in a way contrary to Gods command, though he gets nothing therby but his own death, and their empty commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation <note n="(l)" place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 35. <hi>v.</hi> 21.22 23.</note> Conſpiracy, which is a plot againſt the Common-wealth, (as <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> hath defined it) this they call fighting for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, and yet impudently affirme what <hi>Auguſtine</hi> of Heretiques [<hi>Nihilaliud laborant, niſi non invenire quod quaerunt</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Auguſt. Tom. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>516.1.</hi>
               </note>] that the end of their ſweat, expence and hazard, is not to enjoy what they ſeeme to fight for, <hi>viz.</hi> the Proteſtant Religion in its truth, purity and univerſality: and there are (I dare ſay) many thouſands of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts and Libertines now in armes, which were they put to their oathes would confeſſe thus much. 'Twas madneſſe, ſay they, and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous in <hi>Nero</hi> to ſet <hi>Rome</hi> on fire, and afterwards ſing and rejoyce at the flames, yet theſe very ſame men, Ieſuites happily and Ieſuited per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, have of late ſet three Kingdomes on fire, and whether they laugh at the flames I know not, ſure I am they continually adde fuell to them: yet this cumbuſtion they call a pretended reconciliation, and boaſt themſelves in it. To delude and miſuſe a ſweet and faſt friend, hath ſomewhat of <hi>Iudas</hi> in it, ſay they, yet ſo to intangle their beſt and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:53814:26"/>greateſt friend, as <hi>Darius</hi> his baſe Courtiers entangled him, (<hi>quod eo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ventum eſt, ut tam periculoſum non credere ſuis, quam falli</hi> 
               <note n="(n)" place="margin">Q. curt. l. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> That it is equally dangerous to him not to beleeve them, and to be deceived; this they call their maſter-piece of wiſedome, and boaſt themſelves in it; theſe, theſe are they which are come to ſuch a height of Atheiſme, which a re ſo much beaten and hardened in their ſubtle hypocritical maximes, that they will not move one ſtep out of the way, which the Devil &amp; <hi>Machiavill</hi> have chalkt out to them; and ſo reſolute and petemptory too in that way, that we may ſay of them as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> of Heretiques (<hi>facilius eos vinci quàm perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deri</hi> 
               <note n="(o)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ad Hier. lib contra Lucif.</note> 'Tis eaſier to overcome, then alter them. Thus have I made ſome diſcovery, greater might have beene, had I not promiſed brevity, of the mad, prodigious, deſperately for lorne boaſters of our land, that you might admire, and lament the miſerable condition of our times. But oh! take heed that you be not ſo loſt in admiration, that you forget to lament, like a gazing childe made forgetfull of his chiefeſt errand, for to this end was the diſcovery made, (God knowes my conſcience) not to make them a laughing, but a mourning ſtocke, that you might be humbled in behalfe both of them, and our land. For hereby ſhall you ſecure your ſelves how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oever they eſcape, or the Kingdome for their ſakes <note n="(p)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 14. <hi>ad</hi> 6.</note> And ſo much of the ſecond Queſtion, I ſhould now forward to the third and laſt, but the time hath much over-run me, let us therfore take up here from this Text &amp; forward, to that other before me, a Text like wiſe ſpeaking the frailty and nothingneſſe of man. For if you deſire farther ground for theſe queſtions, Lo this ſpectacle of mortality may be it; a wiſe, able, ſtrong Gentleman ſuddenly cut off, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> tels you, that our footing in this world being ſo ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, 'tis folly for ſuch fraile weak men as we are, to boaſt; which tels you, that wealth, wit, and friends in the laſt, &amp; needfulleſt times failing, 'tis fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to boaſt of them; which tels you that now he is gone, the common voyce, neither hurts nor pleaſures him, neither leſſens nor addes to his joy; 'tis folly therefore to hunt after it. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> wiſhes us <hi>ſo to run that we may obtaine,</hi> ſo to runne, not as one that beateth the ayre in vaine, for the applauſe of the giddy multitude, but for a prize, for an <hi>incorruptible Crown</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 25.</note> Again ſo run, our life here compared to a reace, not onely for its ſhortneſſe, which is a few paces, but for its trouble ſomeneſſe alſo, 'tis a running, which is no ordinary paine and toyle: Truly therefore ſpake the Patriarch <hi>not onely few but evill alſo are my dayes</hi> 
               <note n="(ſ)" place="margin">Gen. 47.5.</note>: this race ſome give over at their firſt ſetting out, children dying in their Gradles: others after a pace or two paſt, in their youth: ſome in the mid-way, in their beſt man-hood are cut off: moſt, as this our friend, are out of breath ere they reach the ſtayed paces of threeſcore yeares. Let us not therefore boaſt <hi>[canere ante victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arn]</hi> vaunt as though we had obtained the prize, ere we come to our jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:53814:27"/>end: but let us ſo run, ſo zealouſly, and ſo humbly, working forth our ſalvation with feare and trembling, that we may obtaine. If you are not yet ſatisfied, but deſire more ground for my Queſtions, Loe here a ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of humility before you.</p>
            <p>And thus am I fallen upon my laſt meſſage, a meſſage I am confident God wiſht me to deliver; namely, to recall and make known ſomethings excellent, and exemplary from the life and death of my worthy friend, I ſay it againe, my worthy friend. I may not boaſt, my Text forbids it, but I joy in our paſt relation <note n="*" place="margin">Amaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur a me plurimùm nec tamen vicius. Plin. l. <hi>2.</hi> Ep. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> And here I would not be miſtaken, conclude not ſo unworthily of me, that his wealth, place, or friends, put mee on this diſcourſe, though to ſpeake truely, ſo runnes the faſhion of the world: if a man be poore, though never ſo good and holy, yet ſhall he paſſe away in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, as we find nothing ſaid of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> but that he dyed, whereas it is ſaid there of the rich man, not onely that he dyed, but that he was buried too <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.22.</note>, ſaith a Commentator of ours, there was noyſe and pompe, much done and ſaid at his Funerall: So many [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] ſhall you have, many Hack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney praiſers in black, which at the Funerals of great and rich men, though they departed as gluttonous, as mercileſſe as <hi>Dives,</hi> never leave prating till they have plac't them in heaven. But I know where I am, I know not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in whoſe preſence, but in whoſe ſtead I ſtand, of what therefore I am to ſpeak, let me uſe <hi>Iobs</hi> words. <hi>Loe mine eyes have ſeene all this, mine eares have heard and underſtood it, what you know, the ſame do I know alſo</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 13.1.2.</note> And as in my following diſcourſe I am reſolved to be true, ſo am I neceſſarily forc'd to be briefe, &amp; for theſe reaſons. Firſt, becauſe of my preſent weaknes; Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the ſcantling of time allowed me as for meditaton, ſo now for delivery; Thirdly and laſtly, to be otherwiſe, I ſhould much injure my gone friend, who was a profeſt enemy to multitude of words; and alas, why ſhould wee with an overlarge diſcourſe keep our griefes awake, &amp; wounds a bleeding? Why ſhould we ſpeak much of him whom we can no longer enjoy, unleſs it be the more to trouble us that we cannot enjoy him? Briefely and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then thus much.</p>
            <p>I intend not here a genealogy, to acquaint you with his birth &amp; deſcent, this is the Heraulds buſineſſe, &amp; it were a diſparagement to ſo much worth to be beholding to Anceſtours for a commendation, for armes, and titles, —<hi>Vix ea noſtra voco</hi>— they may not well be called our owne, nor thinke I it matter of weight to acquaint you with his breeding, ſince his converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion confeſt how ingenuous it was: No, nor need I tell you, how deare a husband he was, how tender a father, or how ſweet a neighbour: behold this peale of groanes, and miſt of ſighes, tels me ſo much. And to deale tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, this I purpoſely omit (though hee was excellently glorious in all theſe Relations) leſt I might bethought like the Orators <hi>Pliny</hi> ſpeaks of <note n="(w)" place="margin">Panegy. ad Traian.</note>, to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:53814:27"/>upbraid the living of their vices, whilſt I commemorate the vertues of the dead. Theſe five more eminent excellencies I ſhall commend to your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories and imitations.</p>
            <p>The firſt is humility, which conſidering his breeding, parts, place, and calling was admirable: I cannot call to minde that word, looke, or action that ever ſpake him proud: nor was he one of our cunning boaſters, who oft in their own diſpraiſes notably vaunt it, challenge the loweſt place, that they may be forc't to the higheſt, unawares often ſpeak truth, cry [alas they are no-body,] even then tempting ſome baſe Sycophant with the expence of a lie or two to make them Some-body. Nor was he like him, of whom <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>[arte quâda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oſtentator]</hi> an artificiall boaſter. For this I counted his great fault, even <hi>(celata virtus)</hi> that through a natural reſervednes he did not ſo ſhine forth before men, as juſtly he might, and was required of him.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, his true heartedneſſe; a fitter man to make a friend of I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet knew; oh, he was wiſe, and faithfull, hee did not quickly knit the knot, not eaſily familiar, and intimate, but once having made it, he was ſure and faſt: not only was his mouth open to his friend in advice, comfort, and juſt encouragement, but his hands and purſe too for reliefe and ſuccour; no nor his mouth and purſe only, but his heart alſo, willing was he to enlarge his joyes by communicating them, and eaſe his grief by venting; and this, this openneſs eſpecially ſpeaks a true friend, whence our Saviour to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>Henceforth I call you not Servants, for the ſervant knoweth not his Lords will, but I have called you friends;</hi> and mark the reaſon; <hi>for all things that I have heard of my Father I have made known unto you</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.15.</note>: The other two of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of friendſhip may be diſſembled; I may through a ſelf-end teach my tongue Parat-like to prate the language of love, when my heart ſwels and repines at what it ſayes. I may again, through a ſelf-end hazard my goods and credit, and my life too ſeemingly in the behalf of my friend, when 'tis nothing ſo; as there are ſome, I am confident, at this preſent which pretend the honour and ſafety of their deceiv'd friend, and under this pretence mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant-like venture both lives and fortunes, when in truth and indeed their only aime is liberty for their profaneneſs and toleration, if not admittance, for their hereſie: as <hi>Hierome</hi> of <hi>Jovinians</hi> Diſciples, <hi>(non tam te loquentem ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantur, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vitiis ſuis favent)</hi> ſo I of theſe, they do not ſo much adhere to their friend, as favour their own vices. But I cannot diſſemble either my own friendſhip, or ſuſpect another, when I freely open my boſome unto him; and this did he often unto his friend, this to my ſelf not only in his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as to his Miniſter, but in his health as to his friend: He left it to weaker leſſe knowing men, who skill'd not to chuſe a friend, to make uſe of <hi>Bias</hi> his wiſe adviſe, <hi>(ama tanquam oſurus)</hi> to love ſo reſervedly, that in chance of a breach, you may not lie at the mercy of your ſuppoſed friend, leſt when he
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:53814:28"/>proves a knave, you prove your ſelf a fool in being ſo groſly miſtake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in him.</p>
            <p>The third, his temperance; and that in meat, drink, and recreations; the covenant <hi>Iob</hi> made with his eyes <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 31.1.</note>, he made with his appetite alſo, to keep himſelfe unſpotted of uncleanneſs, gluttony and drunkenneſs; the feare <hi>Iob</hi> had of his ſorrows <note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 9.28.</note>, he had of all his paſſions; even in ſickneſſe, even in his extreameſt fits I could not diſcover the leaſt token of fear or anger, except it was the feare of God, &amp; an holy indignation againſt himſelfe for ſin. This vertue was moſt eminently exemplary in him, and God forbid, that the neglect of ſo excellent a pattern ſhould aggravate both your ſins and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yours eſpecially, to whom by reaſon of your neare relations, this grace ſhined out moſt gloriouſly. For my part it is my wiſh, and ſhall be my prayer, that his example may be of like force with <hi>Amaziah's,</hi> of whoſe Son it is Regiſtred <note n="a" place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 15.3.</note>, <hi>That he was right in the ſight of the Lord, and did according to all that his father Amaziah had done before him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth, his providence, care, and induſtry in the employment of that ſtock, talent, and calling the Lord had given him. To prove this I have a double argument, the voyce of the Court, whereof hee was a grave member: And this it was, of which I have been an eare-witneſſe, none more exact, more carefull, more faithfull then hee: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the bleſſing of God upon his honeſt endeavours, the Lord crown'd it with a large portion, and his lot fell in a faire ground. But en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy may object; this rather an argument of covetouſneſſe then providence; 'tis to be feared he made too much haſt to be rich, and therfore could not be innocent, getting ſo much in ſo little time. Into this ſnarling mouth I fling theſe anſwers. Firſt, his time of thriving was no little time, he was a long gatherer, and ever frugall; and ſecondly, he had many occaſionall additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to his eſtate," and is well known to you all: This to free him from making too much haſt to bee rich. Again that he was not covetous, theſe reaſons prove: Firſt, he diſlik't, ſure I am, ever ſince I knew him, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt griping trade of uſury: Secondly, he never made purchaſe, as I have heard not himſelfe only, but ſome neighbours affirm, wherein he gave not of the moſt: Thirdly and laſtly, he was liberall at his door, and hoſpitable in his houſe: Whoſoever ſhall be apt to condemn him out of this opinion, that thrift and providence, and the Lords bleſſing on theſe, a joyning houſe to houſe, and land to land, cannot be without covetouſneſſe, this man is much out of the way: The truth doutbleſſe is quite of the other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, thoſe which are careleſſe of their own eſtates are moſt covetous of their neighbours, witneſſe <hi>Cataline,</hi> of whom <hi>Saluſt [ſui profuſus, alieni appetens,]</hi> men oft ſpend that wit and time in taking from others, which ſhould have been imployed in keeping or encreaſing their own, becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming thus at the ſame time theeves, and loyterers: Some the deſire of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:53814:28"/>goods, and skill in cheating, leaves them careleſſe of their own; others againe waſting their own eſtates become covetous of their neighbours.</p>
            <p>The fifth, as the laſt and chiefeſt; his conſtancy in the obſervation of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious dayes and duties; never ſince God ſent me to you, doe I remember, that ever he abſented himſelfe from our holy meeting, unleſſe ſickneſſe or ſome undeniable and lawfull occaſion detained him; conſtantly did he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſet times of prayer in his Family. And ſo punctuall was he in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Lords own day, that when the violent danger of a fit, and the earneſtneſſe of his friends (his Miniſter urging reaſons for it) could not be perſwaded that a Meſſenger ſhould on that holy day travell for a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, no not after our publike devotions were ended. But his Religion wil more brightly appeare, when as in the laſt and next place, you ſhall heare how religiouſly and thriftily he husbanded the time of his ſickneſſe.</p>
            <p>Which was almoſt nothing elſe but a continued prayer, a praying al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, a praying without ceaſing. For his ſickneſſe ſeized him with ſuch violence, &amp; deadly ſymptomes, that it told him at firſt what he was to look for, wherefore he preſently pronounced [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] unto himſelf, reſolv'd for death, and thereupon forthwith betook himſelf unto God in a long and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous prayer, and unleſſe it were in ſome neceſſary intermiſſions of reſt, of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving either ſpirituall or temporall food and Phyſick, he continued in the ſame poſture and action untill his laſt fit, which took him away praying: Nay, when he was quite tyred with the extremity of his fit, &amp; ſleep offered it ſelfe, he would oft refuſe it, ſaying, he could not ſpare ſo much time from his devotions; and when I anſwered him that by reſt he would be the better fitted and quickned for prayer, he replyed, but (oh!) I ſhal have ill thoughts get within me even in my ſleep to my great hinderance: at laſt when I told him that ſuch ill thoughts, that ſeized on him thus unwillinly, and were ſuddenly ſorrowed for, awaking would as ſoon vaniſh and be pardoned; he was with much difficulty brought to admit of an houres intermiſſion for that reſt, which he ſo much wanted: Yet even then too did he manifeſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf part of the Church (of Chriſts Spouſe) <hi>who though ſhe ſlept, yet her heart waked</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Cant. <hi>5.2.</hi>
               </note> for ſeemingly to us aſleep, yet many times the up-moving of his hands ſhowed his heart was awaked unto God. But when he was perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly awaked, with ſuch earneſtneſſe even in his extreameſt fits did he faſten his eyes, and hands, and heart too, (I dare ſay) towards heaven, that I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve 'twas with him as with <hi>Stephen</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Acts <hi>7.56.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>By faith he ſaw the heavens opened, and the Son of man ſtanding on the right hand of God,</hi> whom he then ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly plyed to pray the Father for him. He came at laſt to ſuch a delight in prayer, that ſpending one whole almoſt even a terrible night of many threatning fits in this heavenly Colloquy and familiarity with God; and I asking him the morrow following, how he had ſped that night: Oh ſaid
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:53814:29"/>he, I have had many brave fits, and told me withall that God would not let him loſe one fit, but ever after it he found his faith and comfort en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing, The Lord by them does work me (ſaid he) and by degrees I creep unto him.</p>
            <p>When we firſt ſate about the great buſineſſe of preparation for death, which truth is, ought to be the buſineſſe and task of our whole life, I could not take the courſe uſuall with me on the like occaſions: firſt, to adminiſter the Law, its exactneſs, terrors and curſes on the diſobedience, allowing ſome certain time and dayes for the working of it, ere I adminiſtred the Goſpel: but by reaſon of the danger his fits threatned, I was forc't to make a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the Law and Goſpel, to adminiſter them mingled, and compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, acquainting him at the ſame time with terrours and comforts, threats and promiſes, hell and heaven, leſt he might have been ſuddenly cut off in a deſperate ſorrow, or a falſe joy. And (God bee prayſed) accordingly it wrought with him; now you ſhould have his eyes faſtened on the ground in token of humiliation, anon piercing the Heavens in token of confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; now you ſhould have his hands wrung in token of griefe, anon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, held up in token of hope; now a teare in token of ſorrow, and then a ſmile in token of joy; juſt like this Month of <hi>April,</hi> raine and Sun-ſhine, ſtormes and calm. But towards his end, theſe enter changes ceaſt, the calm begun to be full and glorious; he might have cryed out with the Church <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.11 12.</note>, <hi>Lo, the winter is paſt, the raine is over, the flowers appeare on the earth, the time of the ſinging of birds is come, the voyce of the Turtle is heard.</hi> For I ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him whether or no his comfort did encreaſe, he anſwered me, <hi>excellent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, greatly;</hi> and how faith held out, hee replyed, <hi>ſtrongly,</hi> even then when I could ſcarce hear him: Whereupon demanding of him (loath I was the the Devill ſhould at laſt gull him) whether he could at the preſent reſiſt unto blood, be burnt, undergoe the fiery tryall for his Saviours cauſe and glory; he anſwered me, <hi>gladly, gladly.</hi> Laſtly, the Lord ſo much ſhewed himſelf unto him, gave him ſo full a view of his treaſures, ſuch a largetaſte of thoſe joyes that were laid up for him in heaven (as wee are charitably given to believe) that he underwent the extremity of his fits not with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience only, but with comfort, and left the world, (his wealth, friends and pleaſures) not out of a dull ſenſe of the paine and agony of his ſickneſſe or a prophetick ſenſibleneſſe of the miſcries falling on this Kingdom, (which he would oft lament) nor made he in this reſpect a vertue of neceſſity, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly left it becauſe he could no longer enjoy it: this were like a condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thiefe or traytor, who ſeem willing to lay down their lives, becauſe they can no longer keep them: not in this, or that, or the other falſe reſpect did he welcome death, but therefore was with joy and cheerfulneſſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, becauſe his faith aſſured him he ſhould be with Chriſt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
